뭐가 신기한지 아세요?
You know what's crazy?
이 모든 게 실제로
일어나고 있다는 거요.
That all of this is real.
무슨 의미인가요?
Meaning what?
그렇게 생각 안 하세요?
Don't you think so?
이 모든 AI 이야기랑 베이 에어리어
All this AI stuff and all this Bay Area… that it's happening.
일들이… 실제로 일어나고 있다는 거요.
완전히 SF 같지 않나요?
Isn't it straight out of science fiction?
또 신기한 건, '느린 이륙'이
이렇게 평범하게 느껴진다는 거예요.
Another thing that's crazy is how normal the slow takeoff feels.
GDP의 1%를 AI에
투자한다는 게 훨씬 더
The idea that we'd be investing 1% of GDP in AI, I feel like it would have felt like a bigger deal, whereas right now it just feels...
큰 일처럼 느껴졌을 것
같은데, 지금은 그냥…
사람은 생각보다 빨리 적응하나 봐요.
We get used to things pretty fast, it turns out.
근데 또 좀 추상적이기도 해요.
But also it's kind of abstract.
그게 무슨 뜻인가요?
What does it mean?
뉴스에서 어느 회사가 얼마를 투자한다고
It means that you see it in the news, that such and such company announced such and such dollar amount.
발표했다더라, 그런
걸 보게 된다는 거죠.
보이는 건 그게 다예요.
That's all you see.
지금까지는 다른 방식으로는
딱히 체감되지 않아요.
It's not really felt in any other way so far.
아예 여기서부터 시작해 볼까요?
Should we actually begin here?
흥미로운 주제인 것 같아요.
I think this is an interesting discussion.
좋아요.
Sure.
평범한 사람 입장에선 별로
달라진 게 없다는 그
I think your point, about how from the average person's point of view nothing is that different, will continue being true even into the singularity.
말씀은, 특이점에 이르러서도
계속 사실일 것 같아요.
아니요, 저는 그렇게 생각 안 해요.
No, I don't think so.
아, 흥미롭네요.
Okay, interesting.
제가 체감이 안 된다고 말씀드린
건, 어느 회사가 가늠하기
The thing which I was referring to not feeling different is, okay, such and such company announced some difficult-to-comprehend dollar amount of investment.
힘든 액수의 투자를
발표했다더라, 그런 거였어요.
그 정보로 뭘 해야 할지
아는 사람은 없을 거예요.
I don't think anyone knows what to do with that.
하지만 AI의 영향은
체감될 거라고 생각해요.
But I think the impact of AI is going to be felt.
AI가 경제 전반에 확산될 거예요.
AI is going to be diffused through the economy.
여기엔 아주 강한 경제적
힘이 작용할 거고,
There'll be very strong economic forces for this, and I think the impact is going to be felt very strongly.
그 영향은 아주 강하게
체감될 거라고 봐요.
그 영향은 언제쯤 나타날 거라고 보세요?
When do you expect that impact?
모델들이 경제적 영향이 보여주는
것보다 더 똑똑해 보이는 것 같아요.
I think the models seem smarter than their economic impact would imply.
네.
Yeah.
이게 지금 모델들을 두고 정말
혼란스러운 지점 중 하나예요.
This is one of the very confusing things about the models right now.
평가(evals)에서는 이렇게 잘하는데,
How to reconcile the fact that they are doing so well on evals?
그 사실을 어떻게 이해해야 할까요?
평가를 보면 '이거 꽤
어려운 평가네' 싶어요.
You look at the evals and you go, "Those are pretty hard evals."
그런데 정말 잘 해내거든요.
They are doing so well.
그런데 경제적 영향은 훨씬
뒤처져 있는 것 같고요.
But the economic impact seems to be dramatically behind.
어떻게 모델이 한편으론 이렇게 놀라운
일을 해내면서, 다른 한편으론 어떤
It's very difficult to make sense of, how can the model, on the one hand, do these amazing things, and then on the other hand, repeat itself twice in some situation?
상황에서는 같은 일을 두 번
반복하는지, 이해하기가 정말 어려워요.
예를 들어 바이브 코딩으로
뭔가를 만든다고 해볼게요.
An example would be, let's say you use vibe coding to do something.
어딘가에서 버그가 하나 생겨요.
You go to some place and then you get a bug.
그럼 모델한테 "이 버그
좀 고쳐줄래?"라고 말하죠.
Then you tell the model, "Can you please fix the bug?"
그럼 모델이 "아,
정말 맞는 말씀이세요.
And the model says, "Oh my God, you're so right.
저한테 버그가 있었네요.
I have a bug.
고쳐볼게요"라고 해요.
Let me go fix that."
그러면서 두 번째 버그를 만들어내죠.
And it introduces a second bug.
그래서 "이번엔 새로 생긴
이 두 번째 버그요"라고
Then you tell it, "You have this new second bug," and it tells you, "Oh my God, how could I have done it?
하면, 모델은 "아이고,
제가 어쩌다 그랬을까요.
다시 한번 정말 맞는
말씀이세요"라면서 첫 번째 버그를
You're so right again," and brings back the first bug, and you can alternate between those.
도로 가져와요. 그렇게 계속
왔다 갔다 하는 거죠.
어떻게 그런 일이 가능한 걸까요?
How is that possible?
확실친 않지만, 뭔가 이상한 일이
벌어지고 있다는 건 분명해요.
I'm not sure, but it does suggest that something strange is going on.
가능한 설명이 두 가지 있어요.
I have two possible explanations.
좀 더 엉뚱한 설명은, 어쩌면
강화학습(RL) 훈련이 모델을 지나치게
The more whimsical explanation is that maybe RL training makes the models a little too single-minded and narrowly focused, a little bit too unaware, even though it also makes them aware in some other ways.
한 가지에만 몰두하게 만들고 시야를
좁혀서, 어떤 면에서는 인식을
더 키워주면서도 다른 면에서는
오히려 좀 둔감하게 만든다는 거예요.
그래서 기본적인 것들을 못 하는 거고요.
Because of this, they can't do basic things.
하지만 또 다른 설명도 있어요.
But there is another explanation.
사전학습(pre-training)을
하던 시절에는
Back when people were doing pre-training, the question of what data to train on was answered, because that answer was everything.
'어떤 데이터로 학습할
것인가'라는 질문에 이미
답이 나와 있었어요. 답이
'전부 다'였으니까요.
사전학습을 할 때는 모든
데이터가 필요해요.
When you do pre-training, you need all the data.
그러니 이 데이터로 할지 저
데이터로 할지 고민할 필요가 없죠.
So you don't have to think if it's going to be this data or that data.
하지만 사람들이 RL 훈련을
할 때는 고민이 필요해요.
But when people do RL training, they do need to think.
"좋아, 이건 이런 RL 훈련으로, 저건
They say, "Okay, we want to have this kind of RL training for this thing and that kind of RL training for that thing."
저런 RL 훈련으로
하자"고 말하는 거죠.
제가 듣기로는 모든
회사에 새로운 RL 환경만
From what I hear, all the companies have teams that just produce new RL environments and just add it to the training mix.
만들어서 훈련 믹스에
추가하는 팀이 있대요.
질문은, 그게 대체 뭐냐는 거죠.
The question is, well, what are those?
자유도가 너무 많아요.
There are so many degrees of freedom.
만들 수 있는 RL 환경의
종류가 정말 다양하죠.
There is such a huge variety of RL environments you could produce.
할 수 있는 한 가지는, 이건
의도치 않게 벌어지는 일
One thing you could do, and I think this is something that is done inadvertently, is that people take inspiration from the evals.
같은데, 사람들이 평가(evals)에서
영감을 얻는 거예요.
"자, 우리 모델이 출시될
때 정말 잘했으면 좋겠다.
You say, "Hey, I would love our model to do really well when we release it.
평가(evals) 결과가
멋지게 나왔으면 좋겠다.
I want the evals to look great.
이 과제에 도움이 될 RL
훈련이 뭘까?"라고 하는 거죠.
What would be RL training that could help on this task?"
이런 일이 실제로
벌어진다고 생각하고, 지금
I think that is something that happens, and it could explain a lot of what's going on.
일어나는 많은 일을
설명할 수 있다고 봐요.
여기에 모델의 일반화가 실제로
부족하다는 점까지 더하면, 지금
If you combine this with generalization of the models actually being inadequate, that has the potential to explain a lot of what we are seeing, this disconnect between eval performance and actual real-world performance, which is something that we don't today even understand, what we mean by that.
우리가 목격하는 현상, 즉
평가(evals) 성능과 실제 성능
사이의 이 괴리를 상당 부분
설명할 수 있어요. 사실 이 괴리가
정확히 무엇을 뜻하는지조차 오늘날
우리는 제대로 이해하지 못하고 있죠.
진짜 보상 해킹은
평가(evals)에 매몰된
I like this idea that the real reward hacking is the human researchers who are too focused on the evals.
인간 연구자들이라는 이
생각이 마음에 드네요.
방금 지적하신 부분을 이해하는, 혹은
I think there are two ways to understand, or to try to think about, what you have just pointed out.
생각해보는 방법이 두 가지 있다고 봐요.
하나는, 만약 코딩 대회에서
초인적인 수준이 된다고 해서
One is that if it's the case that simply by becoming superhuman at a coding competition, a model will not automatically become more tasteful and exercise better judgment about how to improve your codebase, well then you should expand the suite of environments such that you're not just testing it on having the best performance in coding competition.
모델이 자동으로 더 감각
있고 코드베이스를 개선할
판단력까지 좋아지는 게
아니라면, 그땐 코딩 대회 최고
성능만 테스트하지 않도록 환경의
폭을 넓혀야 한다는 거예요.
X나 Y나 Z를 위한 최고의
애플리케이션도 만들 수 있어야 하는 거죠.
It should also be able to make the best kind of application for X thing or Y thing or Z thing.
다른 하나는, 아마 이게
암시하신 부분일 텐데, "애초에
Another, maybe this is what you're hinting at, is to say, "Why should it be the case in the first place that becoming superhuman at coding competitions doesn't make you a more tasteful programmer more generally?"
코딩 대회에서 초인적이
된다고 해서 왜 더 전반적으로
감각 있는 프로그래머가 되지
않는가?"라고 묻는 거예요.
어쩌면 해야 할 일은 환경의
양과 다양성을 계속 쌓는
Maybe the thing to do is not to keep stacking up the amount and diversity of environments, but to figure out an approach which lets you learn from one environment and improve your performance on something else.
게 아니라, 한 환경에서
배운 걸 다른 것의 성능
향상으로 이어지게 하는 접근법을
찾는 걸 수도 있어요.
도움이 될 만한 인간
유비가 하나 있어요.
I have a human analogy which might be helpful.
말씀하신 김에 경쟁 프로그래밍의
경우를 예로 들어보죠.
Let's take the case of competitive programming, since you mentioned that.
학생 두 명이 있다고 해보죠.
Suppose you have two students.
한 명은 최고의 경쟁 프로그래머가 되기로
One of them decided they want to be the best competitive programmer, so they will practice 10,000 hours for that domain.
마음먹고, 그 분야에서
1만 시간을 연습해요.
모든 문제를 풀고, 모든
증명 기법을 암기하고, 모든
They will solve all the problems, memorize all the proof techniques, and be very skilled at quickly and correctly implementing all the algorithms.
알고리즘을 빠르고 정확하게
구현하는 데 아주 능숙해지죠.
그렇게 해서 그 학생은
최고 중 한 명이 됐죠.
By doing so, they became one of the best.
두 번째 학생은 '오, 경쟁 프로그래밍
재밌겠다' 정도로 생각했어요.
Student number two thought, "Oh, competitive programming is cool."
아마 100시간 정도, 훨씬 적게
연습했는데도 역시 아주 잘했어요.
Maybe they practiced for 100 hours, much less, and they also did really well.
둘 중 누가 나중에 커리어에서
더 잘할 것 같으세요?
Which one do you think is going to do better in their career later on?
두 번째요.
The second.
맞아요.
Right.
저는 기본적으로 그게 지금
벌어지고 있는 일이라고 생각해요.
I think that's basically what's going on.
모델들은 첫 번째 학생과 훨씬 더
비슷한데, 그 정도가 더 심해요.
The models are much more like the first student, but even more.
왜냐하면 우리는 '모델이 경쟁
프로그래밍을 잘해야 하니까
Because then we say, the model should be good at competitive programming so let's get every single competitive programming problem ever.
존재하는 모든 경쟁 프로그래밍
문제를 다 모으자'라고 하거든요.
그리고 데이터 증강까지
해서 경쟁 프로그래밍
And then let's do some data augmentation so we have even more competitive programming problems, and we train on that.
문제를 더 늘리고, 그걸로 학습시키죠.
그러면 이제 엄청난 경쟁
프로그래머가 생기는 거예요.
Now you've got this great competitive programmer.
이 비유로 보니 더
직관적으로 이해되네요.
With this analogy, I think it's more intuitive.
네, 그렇게까지 훈련받았다면
온갖 알고리즘과
Yeah, okay, if it's so well trained, all the different algorithms and all the different proof techniques are right at its fingertips.
증명 기법이 다 손끝에 있는 거네요.
그리고 이 정도로 준비된
상태라면 다른 영역으로 꼭
And it's more intuitive that with this level of preparation, it would not necessarily generalize to other things.
일반화되지는 않는다는 것도
더 직관적으로 와닿아요.
그럼 두 번째 학생이 그
100시간의 파인튜닝을
But then what is the analogy for what the second student is doing before they do the 100 hours of fine-tuning?
하기 전에 하고 있던 건
뭐에 비유할 수 있을까요?
저는 그 학생에게 '그것'이
있었다고 생각해요.
I think they have "it."
'그것'이요.
The "it" factor.
제가 학부생이었을 때, 저랑
같이 공부했던 학생 중에 그런
When I was an undergrad, I remember there was a student like this that studied with me, so I know it exists.
사람이 있었던 게 기억나요.
그래서 그게 실재한다는 걸 알아요.
'그것'을 사전학습이 하는 일과
구분하는 게 흥미롭다고 생각해요.
I think it's interesting to distinguish "it" from whatever pre-training does.
방금 사전학습에서는 데이터를
굳이 골라야 할 필요가
One way to understand what you just said about not having to choose the data in pre-training is to say it's actually not dissimilar to the 10,000 hours of practice.
없다고 하신 걸 이렇게
이해할 수도 있을 것 같아요.
사실 그게 1만 시간의
연습과 그리 다르지 않다고요.
다만 그 1만 시간의
연습을 공짜로 얻는 거죠.
It's just that you get that 10,000 hours of practice for free because it's already somewhere in the pre-training distribution.
이미 사전학습 분포
어딘가에 들어있으니까요.
그런데 어쩌면 말씀하시려는
건 사전학습에서 나오는
But maybe you're suggesting there's actually not that much generalization from pre-training.
일반화가 사실 그렇게 많지
않다는 거 아닐까요.
사전학습에는 그냥 데이터가
엄청 많은 것뿐이지, 그게
There's just so much data in pre-training, but it's not necessarily generalizing better than RL.
RL보다 일반화를 더 잘
시켜준다는 건 아니라는 거죠.
사전학습의 가장 큰 강점은
이거예요. 첫째, 양이
The main strength of pre-training is that: A, there is so much of it, and B, you don't have to think hard about what data to put into pre-training.
정말 방대하다는 것.
둘째, 어떤 데이터를
사전학습에 넣을지 굳이
고민할 필요가 없다는 것이죠.
아주 자연스러운 데이터고, 그
안에는 사람들이 하는 일들,
It's very natural data, and it does include in it a lot of what people do: people's thoughts and a lot of the features.
즉 사람들의 생각과 여러
특성들이 많이 담겨 있어요.
마치 사람들이 세상 전체를
텍스트에 투영해놓은 것과
It's like the whole world as projected by people onto text, and pre-training tries to capture that using a huge amount of data.
같고, 사전학습은 방대한 데이터로
그걸 포착하려는 거예요.
사전학습은 따져보기가 정말
어려운데, 모델이 사전학습
Pre-training is very difficult to reason about because it's so hard to understand the manner in which the model relies on pre-training data.
데이터에 의존하는 방식을
이해하기가 너무 어렵기 때문이에요.
모델이 실수할 때마다,
어쩌다 보니 그게 사전학습
Whenever the model makes a mistake, could it be because something by chance is not as supported by the pre-training data?
데이터로 충분히 뒷받침되지
않아서일 수도 있지 않을까요?
'사전학습이 뒷받침한다'는 건
어쩌면 느슨한 표현일 수도 있어요.
"Support by pre-training" is maybe a loose term.
이 부분에 대해 더 유용하게
보탤 말이 있을지는 모르겠네요.
I don't know if I can add anything more useful on this.
사전학습에 대응하는 인간의
유사물은 없다고 봐요.
I don't think there is a human analog to pre-training.
사전학습에 대응하는 인간의 유사물이
Here are analogies that people have proposed for what the human analogy to pre-training is.
무엇인지, 사람들이
제안한 비유들이 있어요.
그게 왜 틀렸을 수도 있는지
그 생각을 듣고 싶어요.
I'm curious to get your thoughts on why they're potentially wrong.
하나는 사람이 태어나서
18년, 혹은 15년, 13년
One is to think about the first 18, or 15, or 13 years of a person's life when they aren't necessarily economically productive, but they are doing something that is making them understand the world better and so forth.
동안 경제적으로 꼭 생산적이진
않지만, 세상을 더 잘
이해하게 만드는 무언가를
하고 있다고 보는 거예요.
다른 하나는 진화가 30억 년
동안 일종의 탐색을 해온 결과로,
The other is to think about evolution as doing some kind of search for 3 billion years, which then results in a human lifetime instance.
한 인간의 일생이라는 인스턴스가
나온다고 보는 거예요.
이 둘 중 어느 쪽이든 사전학습에
비견될 수 있다고 보시는지 궁금해요.
I'm curious if you think either of these are analogous to pre-training.
사전학습이 아니라면, 인간의 평생에
걸친 학습은 어떤 것이라고 보세요?
How would you think about what lifetime human learning is like, if not pre-training?
이 둘 다 사전학습과
비슷한 면이 있다고 봐요.
I think there are some similarities between both of these and pre-training, and pre-training tries to play the role of both of these.
사전학습은 이 둘의 역할을
동시에 하려는 셈이죠.
하지만 큰 차이점들도 있다고 생각해요.
But I think there are some big differences as well.
사전학습 데이터의 양은
정말, 정말 어마어마해요.
The amount of pre-training data is very, very staggering.
네.
Yes.
그런데 신기하게도 인간은
15년이 지나도, 사전학습
Somehow a human being, after even 15 years with a tiny fraction of the pre-training data, they know much less.
데이터의 극히 일부만 가지고
아는 건 훨씬 적어요.
하지만 아는 건 뭐든, 왠지
훨씬 깊이 알고 있어요.
But whatever they do know, they know much more deeply somehow.
그 나이만 돼도 이미, 우리 AI들이
저지르는 실수는 하지 않죠.
Already at that age, you would not make mistakes that our AIs make.
또 한 가지가 있어요.
There is another thing.
혹시 진화 같은 것 아니냐고
물으실 수도 있겠죠.
You might say, could it be something like evolution?
답은, 그럴 수도 있다는 거예요.
The answer is maybe.
하지만 이 경우엔, 오히려 진화 쪽이
우위에 있을 수도 있다고 생각해요.
But in this case, I think evolution might actually have an edge.
이 사례를 읽었던 기억이 나요.
I remember reading about this case.
신경과학자들이 뇌에 대해
알아내는 한 가지 방법은, 뇌의
One way in which neuroscientists can learn about the brain is by studying people with brain damage to different parts of the brain.
여러 부위에 손상을 입은
사람들을 연구하는 거예요.
상상도 못 할 만큼 이상한
증상을 겪는 사람들이 있어요.
Some people have the most strange symptoms you could imagine.
정말 굉장히 흥미로운 이야기예요.
It's actually really, really interesting.
그것과 관련해서 떠오르는
사례가 하나 있어요.
One case that comes to mind that's relevant.
뇌졸중이나 사고로 뇌 손상을
입어서 감정을 처리하는
I read about this person who had some kind of brain damage, a stroke or an accident, that took out his emotional processing.
부분이 망가진 사람에 대한
글을 읽은 적이 있어요.
그래서 그는 더 이상 어떤
감정도 느끼지 못하게 됐어요.
So he stopped feeling any emotion.
여전히 말은 또렷하게 잘했고 작은 퍼즐도
He still remained very articulate and he could solve little puzzles, and on tests he seemed to be just fine.
풀 수 있었고, 검사에서도
멀쩡해 보였어요.
하지만 그는 아무
감정도 느끼지 못했어요.
But he felt no emotion.
슬픔도, 분노도, 어떤
활기도 느끼지 못했죠.
He didn't feel sad, he didn't feel anger, he didn't feel animated.
그런데 그는 어쩐 일인지 어떤 결정을
내리는 데도 극도로 서툴러졌어요.
He became somehow extremely bad at making any decisions at all.
양말 한 켤레 고르는 데도
몇 시간이 걸렸어요.
It would take him hours to decide on which socks to wear.
재정적으로도 아주 잘못된
결정을 내리곤 했어요.
He would make very bad financial decisions.
그게 본질적으로, 우리를
제대로 작동하는 행위자로 만드는
What does it say about the role of our built-in emotions in making us a viable agent, essentially?
데 타고난 감정이 어떤 역할을
한다는 걸 말해주는 걸까요?
사전학습에 대한 질문과 연결해보면,
사전학습에서 모든 걸 온전히
To connect to your question about pre-training, maybe if you are good enough at getting everything out of pre-training, you could get that as well.
끌어낼 만큼 잘한다면 그것 역시
얻어낼 수 있을지도 몰라요.
그런데 그건 어쩐지...
But that's the kind of thing which seems...
음, 사전학습에서 그걸 얻는 게
가능할 수도 있고 아닐 수도 있어요.
Well, it may or may not be possible to get that from pre-training.
'그것'이 뭔가요?
What is "that"?
분명히 감정 그 자체는 아니에요.
Clearly not just directly emotion.
어떤 결정에 대해서든 최종
보상이 무엇이어야 하는지를
It seems like some almost value function-like thing which is telling you what the end reward for any decision should be.
알려주는, 거의 가치 함수
같은 무언가로 보여요.
그게 사전학습에서 암묵적으로 나오는
건 아니라고 생각하시는 건가요?
You think that doesn't sort of implicitly come from pre-training?
나올 수도 있다고 생각해요.
I think it could.
그냥 100% 명확한
건 아니라는 거예요.
I'm just saying it's not 100% obvious.
그런데 '그것'이 뭔가요?
But what is that?
감정을 어떻게 생각하세요?
How do you think about emotions?
감정에 대한 ML적 비유는 뭘까요?
What is the ML analogy for emotions?
아마 일종의 가치 함수
같은 것일 거예요.
It should be some kind of a value function thing.
다만 지금 사람들이 하는 일에서
가치 함수가 그렇게 두드러진
But I don’t think there is a great ML analogy because right now, value functions don't play a very prominent role in the things people do.
역할을 하는 게 아니라서, 딱 맞는
ML 비유는 없는 것 같아요.
괜찮으시다면 청취자들을 위해 가치 함수가
It might be worth defining for the audience what a value function is, if you want to do that.
뭔지 정의해 주셔도 좋을 것 같아요.
물론이죠, 기꺼이 설명해 드릴게요.
Certainly, I'll be very happy to do that.
사람들이 강화학습(RL)을 할
때, 그러니까 지금 방식대로
When people do reinforcement learning, the way reinforcement learning is done right now, how do people train those agents?
강화학습이 이뤄질 때, 그
에이전트들을 어떻게 훈련시킬까요?
신경망이 있고, 거기에
문제를 하나 줘요. 그러고
You have your neural net and you give it a problem, and then you tell the model, "Go solve it."
나서 모델한테 "가서
풀어봐"라고 하는 거예요.
모델은 수천, 수십만 번의 행동이나 사고
The model takes maybe thousands, hundreds of thousands of actions or thoughts or something, and then it produces a solution.
같은 걸 거쳐서 답을 하나 내놓아요.
그 답은 채점을 받고요.
The solution is graded.
그리고 그 점수가 궤적 안의 행동
And then the score is used to provide a training signal for every single action in your trajectory.
하나하나에 대한 훈련
신호로 쓰이는 거예요.
그러면 오래 걸리는 일— 푸는 데
시간이 오래 걸리는 과제를 훈련시킬
That means that if you are doing something that goes for a long time—if you're training a task that takes a long time to solve—it will do no learning at all until you come up with the proposed solution.
때는, 최종 답을 내놓을 때까지
학습이 전혀 일어나지 않는다는 뜻이죠.
강화학습을 순진하게 할
때는 이런 식이에요.
That's how reinforcement learning is done naively.
o1, R1도 겉보기엔 이런
식으로 만들어진 것 같고요.
That's how o1, R1 ostensibly are done.
가치 함수는 이런 거예요.
"항상은 아니어도, 가끔은
The value function says something like, "Maybe I could sometimes, not always, tell you if you are doing well or badly."
네가 잘하고 있는지 못하고
있는지 알려줄 수 있어."
가치 함수라는 개념은 어떤 영역에서는
다른 영역보다 더 유용해요.
The notion of a value function is more useful in some domains than others.
예를 들어 체스를 두다가 기물을
잃으면, '아, 망했다' 싶잖아요.
For example, when you play chess and you lose a piece, I messed up.
게임을 끝까지 둬봐야 방금 한 수가
나빴다는 걸 아는 게 아니라,
You don't need to play the whole game to know that what I just did was bad, and therefore whatever preceded it was also bad.
그 전에 한 것들도 나빴다는
걸 바로 알 수 있는 거예요.
가치 함수는 끝까지 기다릴 필요
없이 그 과정을 단축시켜 줘요.
The value function lets you short-circuit the wait until the very end.
수학 문제나 프로그래밍
문제를 풀면서 특정
Let's suppose that you are doing some kind of a math thing or a programming thing, and you're trying to explore a particular solution or direction.
방향이나 풀이를 탐색하고
있다고 해볼게요.
한 1000 스텝 정도 생각한 뒤에, 이
After, let's say, a thousand steps of thinking, you concluded that this direction is unpromising.
방향은 가망이 없다고
결론을 내렸다고 해봐요.
이 결론을 내리는 순간, 사실은
1000 스텝 전— 이 경로를
As soon as you conclude this, you could already get a reward signal a thousand timesteps previously, when you decided to pursue down this path.
택했던 바로 그 시점에 이미 보상
신호를 받을 수 있었던 거예요.
"다음엔 비슷한 상황에서 이
경로를 택하지 말아야겠다"는
You say, "Next time I shouldn't pursue this path in a similar situation," long before you actually came up with the proposed solution.
걸, 실제로 최종 답을 내놓기
훨씬 전에 알 수 있는 거죠.
딥시크 R1 논문에 이런 얘기가
있었는데— 궤적의 공간이 워낙 넓어서,
This was in the DeepSeek R1 paper— that the space of trajectories is so wide that maybe it's hard to learn a mapping from an intermediate trajectory and value.
중간 궤적과 가치 사이의 매핑을
학습하기가 어려울 수도 있다고요.
그리고 예를 들어 코딩할
때는, 잘못된 아이디어를
And also given that, in coding for example you'll have the wrong idea, then you'll go back, then you'll change something.
냈다가 다시 돌아가서
뭔가를 바꾸기도 하잖아요.
그건 딥러닝에 대한 믿음이
너무 없는 말 같은데요.
This sounds like such lack of faith in deep learning.
물론 어려울 수는 있죠. 하지만
딥러닝이 못 할 일은 없어요.
Sure it might be difficult, but nothing deep learning can't do.
제 예상으로는 가치 함수가
분명 유용할 거고, 이미
My expectation is that a value function should be useful, and I fully expect that they will be used in the future, if not already.
쓰이고 있지 않다면 앞으로는
분명 쓰이게 될 거예요.
제가 감정 중추가 손상된 사람
이야기로 암시하려던 건,
What I was alluding to with the person whose emotional center got damaged, it’s more that maybe what it suggests is that the value function of humans is modulated by emotions in some important way that's hardcoded by evolution.
어쩌면 인간의 가치 함수가
진화가 하드코딩해 놓은 방식으로
감정에 의해 중요하게 조절된다는
걸 시사하는 거라는 점이에요.
그리고 그게 사람들이 세상에서 효과적으로
And maybe that is important for people to be effective in the world.
살아가는 데 중요한 걸지도 몰라요.
그게 제가 여쭤보려던 질문이었어요.
That's the thing I was planning on asking you.
가치 함수로서의 감정에 대해
정말 흥미로운 점은, 이해하기엔
There's something really interesting about emotions of the value function, which is that it's impressive that they have this much utility while still being rather simple to understand.
꽤 단순한데도 이 정도로
유용하다는 게 인상적이라는 거예요.
제 답은 두 가지예요.
I have two responses.
저희가 학습시키는 것들, 저희가
얘기하는 그런 종류의 AI에
I do agree that compared to the kind of things that we learn and the things we are talking about, the kind of AI we are talking about, emotions are relatively simple.
비하면 감정이 상대적으로
단순하다는 데는 저도 동의해요.
어쩌면 너무 단순해서
사람이 이해할 수 있는
They might even be so simple that maybe you could map them out in a human-understandable way.
방식으로 지도를 그릴 수
있을 정도일지도 몰라요.
그걸 해보면 멋질 것 같아요.
I think it would be cool to do.
다만 유용성 면에서는 복잡성과
강건성 사이에 트레이드오프가
In terms of utility though, I think there is a thing where there is this complexity-robustness tradeoff, where complex things can be very useful, but simple things are very useful in a very broad range of situations.
있다고 생각해요. 복잡한
건 아주 유용할 수 있지만,
단순한 건 아주 넓은
범위의 상황에서 유용하죠.
지금 보이는 걸 해석하는 한
방법은, 우리 감정 대부분이
One way to interpret what we are seeing is that we've got these emotions that evolved mostly from our mammal ancestors and then fine-tuned a little bit while we were hominids, just a bit.
포유류 조상에게서 진화해 왔고
그다음 인류 조상 단계에서
아주 조금, 정말 조금만
파인튜닝됐다는 거예요.
다만 포유류에겐 없을 법한 사회적
감정은 저희에게 꽤 있어요.
We do have a decent amount of social emotions though which mammals may lack.
하지만 그렇게 정교하지는 않아요.
But they're not very sophisticated.
그리고 정교하지 않기 때문에,
우리가 실제로 살아온
And because they're not sophisticated, they serve us so well in this very different world compared to the one that we've been living in.
세상과는 아주 다른 이런
세상에서도 잘 작동하는 거고요.
사실 실수도 하긴 해요.
Actually, they also make mistakes.
예를 들면 우리 감정이…
For example, our emotions…
음, 사실 잘 모르겠네요.
Well actually, I don’t know.
배고픔도 감정에 들어가나요?
Does hunger count as an emotion?
그건 논쟁의 여지가 있죠.
It's debatable.
하지만 예를 들어 배고픔이라는
직관적 감각은, 먹을 게 풍족한
But I think, for example, our intuitive feeling of hunger is not succeeding in guiding us correctly in this world with an abundance of food.
이 세상에서는 우리를 제대로
이끌어주지 못하고 있다고 생각해요.
사람들은 데이터 스케일링, 파라미터
People have been talking about scaling data, scaling parameters, scaling compute.
스케일링, 컴퓨트 스케일링
얘기를 해왔잖아요.
스케일링을 더 일반적으로
생각할 방법이 있을까요?
Is there a more general way to think about scaling?
다른 스케일링 축은 뭐가 있을까요?
What are the other scaling axes?
제가 맞을 수도 있다고
생각하는 관점이 하나 있어요.
Here's a perspective that I think might be true.
예전에 ML이 돌아가던 방식은,
사람들이 그냥 이것저것
The way ML used to work is that people would just tinker with stuff and try to get interesting results.
만지작거리면서 흥미로운
결과를 얻어보려던 거였어요.
과거에는 그런 식으로 흘러갔던 거죠.
That's what's been going on in the past.
그러다 스케일링에 대한 통찰이 찾아왔죠.
Then the scaling insight arrived.
스케일링 법칙, GPT-3가 나오고 다들
Scaling laws, GPT-3, and suddenly everyone realized we should scale.
스케일링을 해야 한다는
걸 갑자기 깨달았어요.
이건 언어가 사고에 영향을
미치는 하나의 사례예요.
This is an example of how language affects thought.
'스케일링'은 그냥 한
단어지만, 사람들에게 뭘
"Scaling" is just one word, but it's such a powerful word because it informs people what to do.
해야 할지 알려주기 때문에
아주 강력한 단어죠.
다들 "일단 스케일링을
해보자"라고 말하는 거예요.
They say, "Let's try to scale things."
그럼 '뭘 스케일링하지?'라고
묻게 되죠.
So you say, what are we scaling?
사전학습이 바로 스케일링할 대상이었어요.
Pre-training was the thing to scale.
그건 특정한 스케일링 레시피였던 거예요.
It was a particular scaling recipe.
사전학습의 큰 돌파구는 바로 이
레시피가 좋다는 걸 깨달은 거였어요.
The big breakthrough of pre-training is the realization that this recipe is good.
"자, 컴퓨트랑 데이터를
어느 정도 섞어서
You say, "Hey, if you mix some compute with some data into a neural net of a certain size, you will get results.
일정 크기의 신경망에
넣으면 결과가 나옵니다.
그 레시피를 그냥 스케일링하기만 하면
You will know that you'll be better if you just scale the recipe up."
더 좋아질 거라는 것도 알 수 있고요."
이것도 훌륭하죠.
This is also great.
기업들은 이걸 좋아해요, 자원을
투자하는 아주 저위험 방법을 주니까요.
Companies love this because it gives you a very low-risk way of investing your resources.
연구에 자원을 투자하는
건 그보다 훨씬 어렵죠.
It's much harder to invest your resources in research.
한번 비교해보세요.
Compare that.
연구를 한다면 "연구자들이여, 가서
연구해서 뭔가 만들어내라"가 돼야
If you research, you need to be like, "Go forth researchers and research and come up with something", versus get more data, get more compute.
하는데, 그에 비하면 데이터를 더
얻고 컴퓨트를 더 얻는 건 쉽죠.
사전학습에서는 뭔가 나온다는
걸 알 수 있어요.
You know you'll get something from pre-training.
실제로 트위터에서 몇몇 사람들이
하는 말을 보면, 어쩌면 제미나이가
Indeed, it looks like, based on various things some people say on Twitter, maybe it appears that Gemini have found a way to get more out of pre-training.
사전학습에서 더 많은 걸 뽑아내는
방법을 찾은 것처럼 보이기도 해요.
하지만 어느 시점엔 사전학습도
데이터가 바닥날 거예요.
At some point though, pre-training will run out of data.
데이터는 명백히 유한하니까요.
The data is very clearly finite.
그럼 다음엔 뭘 해야 할까요?
What do you do next?
이전과는 다른 레시피로
강화된 사전학습을 하거나,
Either you do some kind of souped-up pre-training, a different recipe from the one you've done before, or you're doing RL, or maybe something else.
강화학습(RL)을 하거나,
아니면 또 다른 뭔가를 하겠죠.
하지만 이제 컴퓨트가 커졌어요,
지금 컴퓨트는 아주 크죠,
But now that compute is big, compute is now very big, in some sense we are back to the age of research.
어떤 의미에서는 우리가 다시
연구의 시대로 돌아온 거예요.
이걸 다르게 표현할
수도 있을 것 같아요.
Maybe here's another way to put it.
2020년까지, 그러니까
2012~2020년은 연구의 시대였어요.
Up until 2020, from 2012 to 2020, it was the age of research.
자, 2020년부터 2025년까지는
스케일링의 시대였죠—그
Now, from 2020 to 2025, it was the age of scaling—maybe plus or minus, let's add error bars to those years—because people say, "This is amazing.
연도엔 오차범위를 좀 두기로
하고요—사람들이 "이거 대단하다.
더 스케일링해야겠다.
You've got to scale more.
계속 스케일링하자"라고 말했으니까요.
Keep scaling."
한 단어로 하면, 스케일링이었죠.
The one word: scaling.
그런데 이제 규모가 정말 커요.
But now the scale is so big.
정말 믿음이 "오, 엄청
크긴 한데, 100배
Is the belief really, "Oh, it's so big, but if you had 100x more, everything would be so different?"
더 있으면 완전히
달라질 거야"인 건가요?
분명 달라지긴 할 거예요.
It would be different, for sure.
그런데 규모를 100배로 늘리면 모든 게
But is the belief that if you just 100x the scale, everything would be transformed?
완전히 바뀔 거라는 게
정말 그 믿음인가요?
저는 그게 사실이라고 생각하지 않아요.
I don't think that's true.
그래서 다시 연구의
시대로 돌아온 거예요,
So it's back to the age of research again, just with big computers.
다만 이번엔 큰 컴퓨터와 함께요.
그거 정말 흥미로운 표현이네요.
That's a very interesting way to put it.
그럼 방금 직접 던지신
질문을 제가 다시 여쭤볼게요.
But let me ask you the question you just posed then.
우리가 스케일링하는 건 정확히 뭐고,
What are we scaling, and what would it mean to have a recipe?
레시피가 있다는 건 무슨 의미일까요?
사전학습에 있었던 것 같은, 물리 법칙에
I guess I'm not aware of a very clean relationship that almost looks like a law of physics which existed in pre-training.
가까운 아주 깔끔한 관계는
저는 잘 모르겠네요.
데이터나 컴퓨트, 파라미터와 손실
사이엔 거듭제곱 법칙이 있었잖아요.
There was a power law between data or compute or parameters and loss.
우리가 찾아야 할 관계는
어떤 종류이고, 이 새로운
What is the kind of relationship we should be seeking, and how should we think about what this new recipe might look like?
레시피가 어떤 모습일지는
어떻게 생각해봐야 할까요?
우리는 이미 한 종류의
스케일링에서 다른 종류의
We've already witnessed a transition from one type of scaling to a different type of scaling, from pre-training to RL.
스케일링으로의 전환을 목격했죠,
사전학습에서 RL로요.
이제 사람들은 RL을
스케일링하고 있어요.
Now people are scaling RL.
트위터에서 사람들이 하는 말을
보면, 지금은 사전학습보다
Now based on what people say on Twitter, they spend more compute on RL than on pre-training at this point, because RL can actually consume quite a bit of compute.
RL에 컴퓨트를 더 많이
쓴다고 해요, RL이
실제로 컴퓨트를 꽤 많이
잡아먹을 수 있으니까요.
아주 긴 롤아웃을
만드니까, 그 롤아웃들을
You do very long rollouts, so it takes a lot of compute to produce those rollouts.
만드는 데 컴퓨트가 많이 들어요.
그런데 롤아웃 하나당
얻는 학습량은 상대적으로
Then you get a relatively small amount of learning per rollout, so you really can spend a lot of compute.
적어서, 정말 컴퓨트를
엄청나게 쓸 수 있는 거죠.
저라면 그걸 스케일링이라고
부르지도 않을 거예요.
I wouldn't even call it scaling.
저는 이렇게 말할 것 같아요,
"자, 지금 뭐 하고 있는 거야?
I would say, "Hey, what are you doing?
지금 하는 게 할 수 있는
일 중 가장 생산적인 일이야?
Is the thing you are doing the most productive thing you could be doing?
컴퓨트를 쓰는 더 생산적인
방법을 찾을 수는 없어?"
Can you find a more productive way of using your compute?"
저희가 앞서 가치 함수
얘기를 했었잖아요.
We've discussed the value function business earlier.
사람들이 가치 함수를
잘 다루게 되면, 아마
Maybe once people get good at value functions, they will be using their resources more productively.
자원을 더 생산적으로 쓰게 될 거예요.
모델을 학습시키는 완전히 다른
방법을 찾아낸다면, 이렇게 말할 수도
If you find a whole other way of training models, you could say, "Is this scaling or is it just using your resources?"
있겠죠. "이게 스케일링인가,
아니면 그냥 자원을 잘 쓰는 건가?"
그러면 좀 애매해지는 것 같아요.
I think it becomes a little bit ambiguous.
그런 의미에서, 예전에
연구의 시대였을 때는 이랬죠.
In the sense that, when people were in the age of research back then, it was, "Let's try this and this and this.
"이것도 해보고, 이것도
해보고, 이것도 해보자.
저것도 해보고, 저것도
해보고, 저것도 해보자.
Let's try that and that and that.
오, 이것 봐, 뭔가
흥미로운 일이 일어나네."
Oh, look, something interesting is happening."
저는 그런 식으로 다시
돌아갈 거라고 봐요.
I think there will be a return to that.
연구의 시대로 돌아온
거라면, 한발 물러서서 봤을
If we're back in the era of research, stepping back, what is the part of the recipe that we need to think most about?
때 레시피에서 가장 고민해야
할 부분은 뭘까요?
가치 함수라고 하셨는데,
사람들은 이미 지금 레시피에
When you say value function, people are already trying the current recipe, but then having LLM-as-a-Judge and so forth.
LLM-as-a-Judge
같은 걸 얹어보고 있잖아요.
그것도 가치 함수라고
할 수 있겠지만, 훨씬
You could say that's a value function, but it sounds like you have something much more fundamental in mind.
더 근본적인 걸 염두에 두신 것 같아요.
사전학습 과정 끝에 단계를
더 붙이는 게 아니라,
Should we even rethink pre-training at all and not just add more steps to the end of that process?
사전학습 자체를 다시 생각해봐야 할까요?
가치 함수에 대한 논의,
흥미로웠던 것 같아요.
The discussion about value function, I think it was interesting.
제가 강조하고 싶은 건, 가치
함수가 RL을 더 효율적으로
I want to emphasize that I think the value function is something that's going to make RL more efficient, and I think that makes a difference.
만들어줄 거라는 거예요. 그리고
그게 차이를 만든다고 봐요.
하지만 가치 함수로 할 수
있는 건 뭐든, 가치 함수
But I think anything you can do with a value function, you can do without, just more slowly.
없이도 할 수 있다고 봐요.
그냥 더 느릴 뿐이죠.
제가 가장 근본적이라고 보는
건, 이 모델들이 어쩐
The thing which I think is the most fundamental is that these models somehow just generalize dramatically worse than people.
일인지 사람보다 일반화를
훨씬 못한다는 거예요.
이건 너무 명백하죠.
It's super obvious.
이게 아주 근본적인 것 같아요.
That seems like a very fundamental thing.
그러니까 핵심은 일반화예요.
So this is the crux: generalization.
여기엔 두 가지 하위 질문이 있어요.
There are two sub-questions.
하나는 샘플 효율성에 관한
거예요. 왜 이 모델들은
There's one which is about sample efficiency: why should it take so much more data for these models to learn than humans?
사람보다 학습하는 데 훨씬
많은 데이터가 필요할까요?
두 번째 질문이 있어요.
There's a second question.
데이터양과는 별개로, 왜
모델에게 원하는 걸 가르치는
Even separate from the amount of data it takes, why is it so hard to teach the thing we want to a model than to a human?
게 사람에게 가르치는
것보다 훨씬 어려울까요?
사람의 경우엔, 굳이 검증
가능한 보상이 없어도…
For a human, we don't necessarily need a verifiable reward to be able to…
지금도 아마 여러 연구자들을
멘토링하고 계실 텐데, 그들과
You're probably mentoring a bunch of researchers right now, and you're talking with them, you're showing them your code, and you're showing them how you think.
이야기하면서 코드도 보여주고,
어떻게 생각하는지도 보여주시잖아요.
그런 모습을 보면서 사고방식과 연구를
어떻게 해야 하는지를 배우는 거죠.
From that, they're picking up your way of thinking and how they should do research.
그 사람들한테 검증 가능한
보상을 정해줄 필요는
You don’t have to set a verifiable reward for them that's like, "Okay, this is the next part of the curriculum, and now this is the next part of your curriculum.
없잖아요, 이런 식으로요.
"자, 이게 커리큘럼의 다음
부분이고, 이제 이게 네
커리큘럼의 다음 부분이야."
"아, 이번 훈련은 불안정했네."
Oh, this training was unstable."
그런 번거롭고 일일이 맞춤 제작해야
하는 과정이 없는 거예요.
There's not this schleppy, bespoke process.
어쩌면 이 두 문제가 실제로는 서로
연결돼 있을 수도 있는데, 저는 두
Perhaps these two issues are actually related in some way, but I'd be curious to explore this second thing, which is more like continual learning, and this first thing, which feels just like sample efficiency.
번째 문제, 그러니까 지속 학습에
더 가까운 것과, 첫 번째 문제,
그러니까 그냥 샘플 효율성처럼 느껴지는
것을 둘 다 탐구해보고 싶어요.
사실 인간의 샘플 효율성에
대해 고려해야 할
You could actually wonder that one possible explanation for the human sample efficiency that needs to be considered is evolution.
가능한 설명 하나로 진화를
떠올려볼 수 있어요.
진화는 우리에게 가능한 한 가장 유용한
Evolution has given us a small amount of the most useful information possible.
정보를 아주 적은 양으로 물려준 거죠.
시각, 청각, 이동 능력 같은
것들에 대해서는, 진화가 우리에게
For things like vision, hearing, and locomotion, I think there's a pretty strong case that evolution has given us a lot.
많은 걸 물려줬다는 주장이
꽤 설득력 있다고 생각해요.
예를 들어 인간의
손재주는 훨씬 뛰어난데…
For example, human dexterity far exceeds…
물론 로봇도 시뮬레이션에서 엄청난 양의
I mean robots can become dexterous too if you subject them to a huge amount of training in simulation.
훈련을 시키면 손재주가
좋아질 수는 있어요.
하지만 사람처럼 실제 세계에서
로봇을 훈련시켜 새로운
But to train a robot in the real world to quickly pick up a new skill like a person does seems very out of reach.
기술을 빠르게 익히게 하는
건 아직 훨씬 멀어 보여요.
여기서 이렇게 말할 수도 있겠죠.
"아, 맞아, 이동 능력."
Here you could say, "Oh yeah, locomotion.
"우리 조상들은 모두 뛰어난 이동
능력이 필요했지, 다람쥐 때부터."
All our ancestors needed great locomotion, squirrels.
"그러니까 이동 능력에
대해서는 우리한테 믿기
So with locomotion, maybe we've got some unbelievable prior."
힘들 정도로 강력한
프라이어가 있을지도 몰라."
시각에 대해서도 같은
주장을 할 수 있어요.
You could make the same case for vision.
제가 알기로는 얀 르쿤이
아이들은 10시간만 연습하면
I believe Yann LeCun made the point that children learn to drive after 10 hours of practice, which is true.
운전을 배운다고 지적한 적이
있는데, 그건 사실이에요.
하지만 우리 시각은 정말 뛰어나죠.
But our vision is so good.
적어도 저는, 다섯 살
때의 제 모습이 기억나요.
At least for me, I remember myself being a five-year-old.
그때 저는 자동차에
완전히 빠져 있었어요.
I was very excited about cars back then.
제 자동차 인식 능력은 다섯 살 때 이미
I'm pretty sure my car recognition was more than adequate for driving already as a five-year-old.
운전하기에 충분하고도
남았을 거라고 꽤 확신해요.
다섯 살짜리는 그렇게 많은
데이터를 접하지 못하잖아요.
You don't get to see that much data as a five-year-old.
대부분의 시간을 부모님 집에서 보내니까,
You spend most of your time in your parents' house, so you have very low data diversity.
데이터 다양성이 아주 낮은 거죠.
하지만 어쩌면 그것도 진화
덕분이라고 말할 수 있어요.
But you could say maybe that's evolution too.
하지만 언어, 수학,
코딩에서는 아마 아닐 거예요.
But in language and math and coding, probably not.
그래도 여전히 모델보다는
나은 것 같아요.
It still seems better than models.
모델이 언어, 수학, 코딩에서는
평균적인 사람보다 나은 게 분명하죠.
Obviously, models are better than the average human at language, math, and coding.
하지만 학습에 있어서도
평균적인 사람보다 나을까요?
But are they better than the average human at learning?
아, 그럼요.
Oh yeah.
네, 확실히 그래요.
Oh yeah, absolutely.
제 말은, 언어·수학·코딩에서,
특히 수학과 코딩에서
What I meant to say is that language, math, and coding—and especially math and coding—suggests that whatever it is that makes people good at learning is probably not so much a complicated prior, but something more, some fundamental thing.
그렇다는 건 사람을 학습에
능하게 만드는 그것이 복잡한
프라이어라기보다는 뭔가 더 근본적인
것임을 시사한다는 거예요.
잘 이해가 안 되네요.
I'm not sure I understood.
왜 그런 거죠?
Why should that be the case?
자, 사람들이 어떤 스킬에서
상당한 신뢰성을 보인다고 해보죠.
So consider a skill in which people exhibit some kind of great reliability.
그 스킬이 수백만 년, 아니
수억 년 동안 우리 조상들에게
If the skill is one that was very useful to our ancestors for many millions of years, hundreds of millions of years, you could argue that maybe humans are good at it because of evolution, because we have a prior, an evolutionary prior that's encoded in some very non-obvious way that somehow makes us so good at it.
정말 유용했던 것이었다면,
인간이 그걸 잘하는 이유는 진화
때문이다, 즉 아주 알기
어려운 방식으로 부호화된 진화적
프라이어가 있어서 그렇게 잘하게
된 거라고 주장할 수 있을 거예요.
하지만 사람들이 최근까지 존재하지도
않았던 영역에서 뛰어난 능력,
But if people exhibit great ability, reliability, robustness, and ability to learn in a domain that really did not exist until recently, then this is more an indication that people might have just better machine learning, period.
신뢰성, 강건성, 학습 능력을
보인다면, 이건 사람이 그냥 더
나은 머신러닝을 갖고 있다는
신호에 더 가까워요. 그게 다예요.
그게 뭔지는 어떻게 생각해봐야 할까요?
How should we think about what that is?
ML로 치면 뭐에 해당하나요?
What is the ML analogy?
흥미로운 지점이 몇 가지 있어요.
There are a couple of interesting things about it.
샘플이 더 적게 들어요.
It takes fewer samples.
더 비지도적이에요.
It's more unsupervised.
아이가 운전을 배운다고 하면…
A child learning to drive a car…
아, 아이들이 운전을 배우는 건 아니죠.
Children are not learning to drive a car.
십 대가 운전을 배울
때, 미리 짜인 검증
A teenager learning how to drive a car is not exactly getting some prebuilt, verifiable reward.
가능한 보상을 딱히 받는 게 아니에요.
그건 기계, 그리고 환경과의
상호작용에서 나오는 거예요.
It comes from their interaction with the machine and with the environment.
샘플이 훨씬 더 적게 들죠.
It takes much fewer samples.
더 비지도적인 것 같고요.
It seems more unsupervised.
더 강건한 것 같은데요?
It seems more robust?
훨씬 더 강건하죠.
Much more robust.
인간의 강건성은 정말 놀라울 정도예요.
The robustness of people is really staggering.
이 모든 게 한꺼번에 일어나는 이유를
Do you have a unified way of thinking about why all these things are happening at once?
하나로 묶어 설명할 방법이 있으신가요?
이런 걸 실현할 수 있는
머신러닝 비유는 뭘까요?
What is the ML analogy that could realize something like this?
질문하신 것 중 하나는, 십대
운전자가 외부 선생님 없이
One of the things that you've been asking about is how can the teenage driver self-correct and learn from their experience without an external teacher?
어떻게 스스로 교정하며
경험에서 배우느냐는 거였죠.
답은, 그들에게 가치
함수가 있다는 겁니다.
The answer is that they have their value function.
전반적인 감각을 갖고 있는데, 사실 이게
They have a general sense which is also, by the way, extremely robust in people.
사람한테는 굉장히 강건하기도 합니다.
인간의 가치 함수가 뭐든
간에, 중독 관련 몇몇
Whatever the human value function is, with a few exceptions around addiction, it's actually very, very robust.
예외를 빼면 실제로
아주, 아주 강건해요.
그래서 예를 들어 운전을 배우는
십대의 경우, 운전을 시작하자마자
So for something like a teenager that's learning to drive, they start to drive, and they already have a sense of how they're driving immediately, how badly they are, how unconfident.
스스로 얼마나 서투른지, 얼마나
자신 없는지 바로 느끼게 되죠.
그러고 나서 "아,
그렇구나" 하고 알게 되고요.
And then they see, "Okay."
그리고 당연히, 십대의 학습
속도는 정말 빠르고요.
And then, of course, the learning speed of any teenager is so fast.
10시간이면 이미 운전할
준비가 되는 거죠.
After 10 hours, you're good to go.
인간에게는 어떤 해법이 있는
것 같은데, 그걸 어떻게
It seems like humans have some solution, but I'm curious about how they are doing it and why is it so hard?
하는 건지, 왜 그렇게
어려운 건지 궁금하네요.
이런 걸 가능하게
하려면 모델을 학습시키는
How do we need to reconceptualize the way we're training models to make something like this possible?
방식을 어떻게 재구상해야 할까요?
좋은 질문이네요, 그리고 제가
의견이 많은 질문이기도 하고요.
That is a great question to ask, and it's a question I have a lot of opinions about.
그런데 안타깝게도, 우리는 모든
머신러닝 아이디어를 자유롭게 논할
But unfortunately, we live in a world where not all machine learning ideas are discussed freely, and this is one of them.
수 없는 세상에 살고 있고, 이게
바로 그런 경우 중 하나예요.
아마 방법이 있을 겁니다.
There's probably a way to do it.
저는 이게 가능하다고 생각해요.
I think it can be done.
사람들이 실제로 그렇다는 사실 자체가,
이게 가능하다는 증거라고 봅니다.
The fact that people are like that, I think it's a proof that it can be done.
다만 다른 장애물이 있을
수도 있는데, 인간 뉴런이
There may be another blocker though, which is that there is a possibility that the human neurons do more compute than we think.
우리 생각보다 더 많은 컴퓨트를
쓸 가능성이 그거예요.
그게 사실이고 중요한 역할을 한다면,
일이 더 어려워질 수도 있고요.
If that is true, and if that plays an important role, then things might be more difficult.
하지만 어쨌든, 이건 제가
의견을 갖고 있는 어떤
But regardless, I do think it points to the existence of some machine learning principle that I have opinions on.
머신러닝 원리가 존재한다는
걸 가리킨다고 봅니다.
다만 안타깝게도, 여건상
자세히 논하기는 어렵네요.
But unfortunately, circumstances make it hard to discuss in detail.
아무도 이 팟캐스트 안 들어요, 일리야.
Nobody listens to this podcast, Ilya.
궁금하네요.
I'm curious.
다시 연구의 시대로 돌아왔다고 하셨는데,
If you say we are back in an era of research, you were there from 2012 to 2020.
2012~2020년에
그 현장에 계셨잖아요.
연구의 시대로 돌아간다면
지금 분위기는 어떨까요?
What is the vibe now going to be if we go back to the era of research?
예를 들어, 알렉스넷 이후에도
실험에 쓰이는 컴퓨트양은
For example, even after AlexNet, the amount of compute that was used to run experiments kept increasing, and the size of frontier systems kept increasing.
계속 늘었고, 프론티어 시스템의
규모도 계속 커졌잖아요.
이제 다시 연구의 시대로 접어들면, 그
Do you think now that this era of research will still require tremendous amounts of compute?
시대도 여전히 엄청난
컴퓨트가 필요할까요?
오래된 자료들을 다시 꺼내 옛
논문들을 읽어야 하게 될까요?
Do you think it will require going back into the archives and reading old papers?
연구 분위기가 더 강했던 시절에 구글,
오픈AI, 스탠퍼드에 계셨잖아요?
You were at Google and OpenAI and Stanford, these places, when there was more of a vibe of research?
커뮤니티에서는 어떤
것들을 기대해야 할까요?
What kind of things should we be expecting in the community?
스케일링의 시대가 낳은 결과
중 하나는, 스케일링이
One consequence of the age of scaling is that scaling sucked out all the air in the room.
방 안의 공기를 전부
빨아들였다는 거예요.
스케일링이 방 안의
공기를 전부 빨아들이다
Because scaling sucked out all the air in the room, everyone started to do the same thing.
보니, 모두가 똑같은
일을 하기 시작한 거죠.
결국 아이디어보다 회사 수가 훨씬
더 많은 세상에 이르렀어요.
We got to the point where we are in a world where there are more companies than ideas by quite a bit.
그것과 관련해서,
실리콘밸리에는 "아이디어는
Actually on that, there is this Silicon Valley saying that says that ideas are cheap, execution is everything.
싸고, 실행이 전부다"라는 말이 있죠.
다들 그렇게 말하고,
거기엔 일리가 있어요.
People say that a lot, and there is truth to that.
그런데 트위터에서 누군가 이런 말을
하는 걸 봤어요. "아이디어가
But then I saw someone say on Twitter something like, "If ideas are so cheap, how come no one's having any ideas?"
그렇게 싸다면, 왜 아무도
아이디어를 못 내는 거지?"
그리고 저는 그것도 맞는
말이라고 생각해요.
And I think it's true too.
연구의 진전을 병목이라는 관점에서
생각해보면, 병목이 여러 개 있어요.
If you think about research progress in terms of bottlenecks, there are several bottlenecks.
하나는 아이디어고, 다른 하나는
그걸 현실로 만드는 능력이에요.
One of them is ideas, and one of them is your ability to bring them to life, which might be compute but also engineering.
이건 컴퓨트일 수도 있고,
엔지니어링일 수도 있고요.
90년대로 돌아가 보면,
꽤 좋은 아이디어를 가진
If you go back to the '90s, let's say, you had people who had pretty good ideas, and if they had much larger computers, maybe they could demonstrate that their ideas were viable.
사람들이 있었어요. 훨씬
더 큰 컴퓨터가 있었다면
그 아이디어가 유효하다는
걸 보여줄 수 있었겠죠.
하지만 그럴 수 없었기
때문에, 아무도 설득
But they could not, so they could only have a very, very small demonstration that did not convince anyone.
못 하는 아주 작은 시연밖에 못 했죠.
그러니까 병목은 컴퓨트였던 거예요.
So the bottleneck was compute.
그러다 스케일링의 시대에
들어서면서 컴퓨트가 크게 늘어났죠.
Then in the age of scaling, compute has increased a lot.
물론 컴퓨트가 얼마나
필요한가 하는 질문은
Of course, there is a question of how much compute is needed, but compute is large.
남아있지만, 컴퓨트 자체는 방대해요.
컴퓨트가 이미 방대해서,
아이디어를 입증하는 데 그보다
Compute is large enough such that it's not obvious that you need that much more compute to prove some idea.
훨씬 더 많은 컴퓨트가
필요한지는 분명하지 않아요.
비유를 하나 들어볼게요.
I'll give you an analogy.
알렉스넷은 GPU 2개로 만들어졌어요.
AlexNet was built on two GPUs.
그게 거기에 사용된 컴퓨트의 전부였죠.
That was the total amount of compute used for it.
트랜스포머는 GPU 8개에서
64개로 만들어졌어요.
The transformer was built on 8 to 64 GPUs.
트랜스포머 논문의 그 어떤 실험도
2017년 기준 GPU 64개를 넘게
No single transformer paper experiment used more than 64 GPUs of 2017, which would be like, what, two GPUs of today?
쓴 적이 없는데, 그게 지금 GPU로
치면 한 2개 정도일 거예요.
ResNet도 있었죠?
The ResNet, right?
o1 추론이 세상에서 가장 컴퓨트가 많이
You could argue that the o1 reasoning was not the most compute-heavy thing in the world.
드는 건 아니었다고 주장할 수도 있죠.
그러니까 연구에는 어느 정도의
컴퓨트가 분명히 필요하지만, 역대
So for research, you definitely need some amount of compute, but it's far from obvious that you need the absolutely largest amount of compute ever for research.
최대 규모의 컴퓨트가 꼭
필요한지는 전혀 명확하지 않아요.
이렇게 주장할 수도 있고, 저도
사실이라고 생각하는데요. 절대적으로
You might argue, and I think it is true, that if you want to build the absolutely best system then it helps to have much more compute.
최고의 시스템을 만들려면 컴퓨트가
훨씬 많은 게 도움이 된다는 거예요.
특히 모두가 같은
패러다임 안에 있을 땐,
Especially if everyone is within the same paradigm, then compute becomes one of the big differentiators.
컴퓨트가 큰 차별화
요소 중 하나가 되죠.
역사를 여쭤보는 이유는, 실제로
그 현장에 계셨기 때문이에요.
I'm asking you for the history, because you were actually there.
실제로 무슨 일이
있었는지는 저도 잘 몰라요.
I'm not sure what actually happened.
최소한의 컴퓨트만으로도 이런 아이디어들을
It sounds like it was possible to develop these ideas using minimal amounts of compute.
개발하는 게 가능했던 것 같네요.
하지만 트랜스포머가 곧바로
유명해진 건 아니었어요.
But the transformer didn't immediately become famous.
점점 더 큰 규모의 컴퓨트에서
검증되면서, 모두가 그걸 쓰기
It became the thing everybody started doing and then started experimenting on top of and building on top of because it was validated at higher and higher levels of compute.
시작하고 그 위에서 실험하고
쌓아 올리기 시작한 거죠.
맞아요.
Correct.
그럼 SSI에 아이디어가
50개 있다고 할 때, 다른
And if you at SSI have 50 different ideas, how will you know which one is the next transformer and which one is brittle, without having the kinds of compute that other frontier labs have?
프론티어 기업들 같은 컴퓨트
없이 그중 어떤 게 다음
트랜스포머고 어떤 게 부실한
아이디어인지 어떻게 알 수 있나요?
그 부분은 제가 말씀드릴 수 있어요.
I can comment on that.
짧게 말씀드리면, 방금
SSI를 언급하셨는데요.
The short comment is that you mentioned SSI.
구체적으로 저희 얘기를 하자면, SSI가
Specifically for us, the amount of compute that SSI has for research is really not that small.
연구용으로 가진 컴퓨트는
사실 그렇게 적지 않아요.
왜 그런지 설명해 드리고 싶어요.
I want to explain why.
간단한 계산만으로도, 저희가
가진 컴퓨트가 연구용으로는
Simple math can explain why the amount of compute that we have is comparable for research than one might think.
생각보다 비슷한 수준이라는
걸 설명할 수 있어요.
설명해 드릴게요.
I'll explain.
SSI는 30억 달러를 조달했는데,
절대적인 기준으로 봐도 큰 금액이죠.
SSI has raised $3 billion, which is a lot by any absolute sense.
하지만 "다른 회사들은 훨씬 더 많이
But you could say, "Look at the other companies raising much more."
조달하잖아"라고 말할 수도 있을 거예요.
하지만 그들의 컴퓨트 중 상당
부분은 인퍼런스로 들어가요.
But a lot of their compute goes for inference.
그 큰 숫자들, 그 큰 대출들은 인퍼런스
These big numbers, these big loans, it's earmarked for inference.
용도로 이미 정해져 있는 거예요.
그게 첫 번째고요.
That's number one.
두 번째로, 인퍼런스를
수행하는 제품을 가지려면
Number two, if you want to have a product on which you do inference, you need to have a big staff of engineers, salespeople.
엔지니어와 영업 인력으로
이루어진 큰 조직이 필요해요.
연구 인력의 상당수가 온갖 제품 관련
기능을 만드는 데 투입돼야 하죠.
A lot of the research needs to be dedicated to producing all kinds of product-related features.
그래서 실제로 연구에 남는 몫을 보면,
그 차이가 훨씬 작아지는 거예요.
So then when you look at what's actually left for research, the difference becomes a lot smaller.
다른 문제는요, 정말 다른
걸 하고 있다면 그걸
The other thing is, if you are doing something different, do you really need the absolute maximal scale to prove it?
증명하는 데 꼭 절대적
최대 규모가 필요한가요?
전혀 그렇지 않다고 봐요.
I don't think that's true at all.
저희 경우엔, 저희가 하는 일이
옳다는 걸 저희 자신에게도,
I think that in our case, we have sufficient compute to prove, to convince ourselves and anyone else, that what we are doing is correct.
다른 누구에게도 증명할 만큼
충분한 컴퓨트가 있다고 봐요.
오픈AI 같은 회사들이
실험에만 지금까지 연간
There have been public estimates that companies like OpenAI spend on the order of $5-6 billion a year just so far, on experiments.
50억~60억 달러 규모를
쓴다는 공개된 추정치가 있었죠.
이건 인퍼런스 등에 쓰는
비용과는 별개의 금액이고요.
This is separate from the amount of money they're spending on inference and so forth.
그러면 연구 실험에만 쓰는 연간 지출이
So it seems like they're spending more a year running research experiments than you guys have in total funding.
SSI의 총 펀딩보다 많은 셈이네요.
그건 그걸로 무엇을
하느냐의 문제라고 봐요.
I think it's a question of what you do with it.
그걸로 무엇을 하느냐의 문제예요.
It's a question of what you do with it.
그들의 경우, 다른 회사들의 경우엔 훈련
In their case, in the case of others, there is a lot more demand on the training compute.
컴퓨트에 대한 수요가 훨씬 더 많아요.
작업 흐름도 훨씬 다양하고 모달리티도
다양하고, 그냥 할 일이 더 많죠.
There’s a lot more different work streams, there are different modalities, there is just more stuff.
그래서 파편화되는 거예요.
So it becomes fragmented.
SSI는 어떻게 돈을 벌 건가요?
How will SSI make money?
이 질문에 대한 제 답은 대략 이래요.
My answer to this question is something like this.
지금은 그냥 연구에 집중하고 있고
그 답은 저절로 드러날 거라고 봐요.
Right now, we just focus on the research, and then the answer to that question will reveal itself.
가능한 답이 여러 개
있을 거라고 생각해요.
I think there will be lots of possible answers.
SSI의 계획은 여전히
초지능으로 직행하는 건가요?
Is SSI's plan still to straight shot superintelligence?
글쎄요.
Maybe.
거기엔 나름의 장점이 있다고 봐요.
I think that there is merit to it.
장점이 많다고 생각하는
게, 일상적인 시장
I think there's a lot of merit because it's very nice to not be affected by the day-to-day market competition.
경쟁에 영향받지 않는다는
게 참 좋거든요.
하지만 계획을 바꾸게 만들 수도
있는 이유가 두 가지 있다고 봐요.
But I think there are two reasons that may cause us to change the plan.
하나는 실용적인 건데, 타임라인이
길어질 경우예요. 그럴 수도 있고요.
One is pragmatic, if timelines turned out to be long, which they might.
둘째, 가장 뛰어나고
강력한 AI가 세상에 나가
Second, I think there is a lot of value in the best and most powerful AI being out there impacting the world.
영향을 미치는 데 큰
가치가 있다고 봐요.
이건 의미 있게 가치
있는 일이라고 생각해요.
I think this is a meaningfully valuable thing.
그러면 왜 기본 계획이
초지능으로 직행하는 건가요?
So then why is your default plan to straight shot superintelligence?
오픈AI, 앤트로픽,
다른 회사들은 명시적으로
Because it sounds like OpenAI, Anthropic, all these other companies, their explicit thinking is, "Look, we have weaker and weaker intelligences that the public can get used to and prepare for."
"보세요, 저희는 점점 약한
지능들을 내놓아서 대중이
익숙해지고 대비하게 합니다"라고
생각하는 것 같거든요.
초지능을 직행으로 만드는 게
왜 더 나을 수 있을까요?
Why is it potentially better to build a superintelligence directly?
찬성 논거와 반대 논거를
둘 다 말씀드릴게요.
I'll make the case for and against.
찬성 논거는, 시장 안에
있을 때 사람들이 마주치는
The case for is that one of the challenges that people face when they're in the market is that they have to participate in the rat race.
어려움 중 하나가 '무한 경쟁'에
참여해야 한다는 거예요.
무한 경쟁이 힘든 건,
힘겨운 트레이드오프에
The rat race is quite difficult in that it exposes you to difficult trade-offs which you need to make.
노출되고 그걸 스스로
감수해야 하기 때문이에요.
"이 모든 것으로부터 우리를 격리하고
연구에만 집중하다가, 준비됐을
It is nice to say, "We'll insulate ourselves from all this and just focus on the research and come out only when we are ready, and not before."
때만, 그전엔 절대 나가지
않겠다"라고 말하는 건 근사하죠.
하지만 반론도 타당하고, 그 둘은 서로
반대 방향으로 작용하는 힘이에요.
But the counterpoint is valid too, and those are opposing forces.
반론은 이래요. "자, 강력한
AI를 세상이 보는 건 유용하다.
The counterpoint is, "Hey, it is useful for the world to see powerful AI.
강력한 AI를 세상이 보는
게 유용한 이유는, 그게
It is useful for the world to see powerful AI because that's the only way you can communicate it."
그걸 전달할 수 있는
유일한 방법이기 때문이다."
음, 꼭 아이디어를
전달할 수 있다는 것만도
Well, I guess not even just that you can communicate the idea— Communicate the AI, not the idea.
아니고— 아이디어가 아니라
AI를 전달하는 거예요.
Communicate the AI.
"AI를 전달한다"는 게 무슨 뜻인가요?
What do you mean, "communicate the AI"?
AI에 관한 에세이를 쓴다고 해보죠.
그 에세이가 "AI는 이렇게
Let's suppose you write an essay about AI, and the essay says, "AI is going to be this, and AI is going to be that, and it's going to be this."
될 거고, 저렇게 될 거고, 또
이렇게 될 거다"라고 말한다고요.
그걸 읽고 "그래, 흥미로운
에세이네"라고 말하죠.
You read it and you say, "Okay, this is an interesting essay."
이제 AI가 이걸 하고, 저걸
하는 걸 실제로 본다고 해보세요.
Now suppose you see an AI doing this, an AI doing that.
비교가 안 되죠.
It is incomparable.
기본적으로 저는 AI가 대중 앞에
있다는 데서 큰 이점이 있다고
Basically I think that there is a big benefit from AI being in the public, and that would be a reason for us to not be quite straight shot.
생각하고, 그게 저희가 완전한
직행을 하지 않을 이유가 될 거예요.
꼭 그것만은 아니지만, 그게
중요한 부분이라고는 생각해요.
I guess it's not even that, but I do think that is an important part of it.
다른 큰 문제는, 인간의 공학과
연구를 통틀어 최종 결과물이 그저
The other big thing is that I can't think of another discipline in human engineering and research where the end artifact was made safer mostly through just thinking about how to make it safe, as opposed to, why airplane crashes per mile are so much lower today than they were decades ago.
'어떻게 안전하게 만들까'라는
생각만으로 더 안전해진 분야를 저는
떠올릴 수 없다는 거예요 —
오히려 오늘날 비행기 사고율이 수십
년 전보다 마일당 왜 훨씬
낮아졌는지를 생각해보면 말이죠.
왜 리눅스에서 버그를 찾는 게 수십
년 전보다 훨씬 어려워졌을까요?
Why is it so much harder to find a bug in Linux than it would have been decades ago?
저는 그게 대부분 이 시스템들이 실제
I think it's mostly because these systems were deployed to the world.
세상에 배포됐기 때문이라고 생각해요.
실패가 발견되고, 그 실패들이
고쳐지면서 시스템이 더 강건해진 거죠.
You noticed failures, those failures were corrected and the systems became more robust.
AGI와 초인적 지능이라고 왜
다를지 저는 잘 모르겠어요. 특히—이
I'm not sure why AGI and superhuman intelligence would be any different, especially given—and I hope we're going to get to this—it seems like the harms of superintelligence are not just about having some malevolent paper clipper out there.
얘기는 나중에 다루면 좋겠는데—초지능의
해악이 단순히 어딘가에
악의적인 페이퍼클립 AI가 있다는
문제만은 아닌 것 같거든요.
이건 정말 강력한 것인데, 사람들이
그것과 어떻게 상호작용할지,
But this is a really powerful thing and we don't even know how to conceptualize how people interact with it, what people will do with it.
사람들이 그걸로 뭘 할지조차 저희는
개념화하는 법을 모르고 있어요.
점진적으로 접근하게 하는 게,
아마 그 영향을 분산시키고
Having gradual access to it seems like a better way to maybe spread out the impact of it and to help people prepare for it.
사람들이 대비하도록 돕는
더 나은 방법인 것 같아요.
음, 이 점에서는 직행
시나리오에서도 결국 점진적으로
Well I think on this point, even in the straight shot scenario, you would still do a gradual release of it, that’s how I would imagine it.
출시하게 될 거라고 생각해요,
제가 상상하기론 그래요.
점진적 접근은 어떤 계획에도
필연적으로 포함될 거예요.
Gradualism would be an inherent component of any plan.
그냥 뭘 제일 먼저
세상에 내놓느냐의 문제죠.
It's just a question of what is the first thing that you get out of the door.
그게 첫 번째고요.
That's number one.
두 번째는, 다른 사람들보다 지속
학습을 더 강하게 주장해오신
Number two, I believe you have advocated for continual learning more than other people, and I actually think that this is an important and correct thing.
걸로 아는데, 저는 이게 중요하고
맞는 얘기라고 생각해요.
이유를 말씀드릴게요.
Here is why.
언어가 사고에 영향을 미치는
또 다른 예를 들어볼게요.
I'll give you another example of how language affects thinking.
이번엔, 모두의 사고를 형성해온 단어
두 개일 거라고 저는 생각해요.
In this case, it will be two words that have shaped everyone's thinking, I maintain.
첫 번째 단어, AGI.
First word: AGI.
두 번째 단어, 사전학습.
Second word: pre-training.
설명해 드릴게요.
Let me explain.
AGI라는 용어, 이게 왜 존재할까요?
The term AGI, why does this term exist?
굉장히 특이한 용어예요.
It's a very particular term.
왜 존재하는 걸까요?
Why does it exist?
이유가 있어요.
There's a reason.
제 생각에 AGI라는 용어가 존재하는
이유는, 지능의 어떤 최종 상태를
The reason that the term AGI exists is, in my opinion, not so much because it's a very important, essential descriptor of some end state of intelligence, but because it is a reaction to a different term that existed, and the term is narrow AI.
나타내는 대단히 중요하고 본질적인
표현이라서가 아니라, 예전에 있었던
다른 용어에 대한 반작용이기 때문이에요.
그 용어가 바로 좁은 AI예요.
체커 AI, 체스 AI,
컴퓨터 게임 AI 같은
If you go back to ancient history of gameplay and AI, of checkers AI, chess AI, computer games AI, everyone would say, look at this narrow intelligence.
게임과 AI의 아득한
역사로 거슬러 올라가 보면,
다들 이렇게 말했죠. "이
좁은 지능 좀 봐."
"체스 AI가 카스파로프를 이길 순
Sure, the chess AI can beat Kasparov, but it can't do anything else.
있어도, 그거 말곤
아무것도 못 하잖아."
"정말 좁다니까. 인공 좁은
지능(artificial
It is so narrow, artificial narrow intelligence.
narrow
intelligence)이지."
그래서 그에 대한
반작용으로, 어떤 사람들은
So in response, as a reaction to this, some people said, this is not good.
이렇게 말했죠. "이건 안 좋다."
"너무 좁다."
It is so narrow.
"우리에게 필요한 건 일반 AI,
그러니까 모든 걸 다 하는 AI다."
What we need is general AI, an AI that can just do all the things.
그 용어가 큰 주목을 받게 된 거죠.
That term just got a lot of traction.
두 번째로 크게 주목받은 건 사전학습,
정확히는 사전학습의 레시피예요.
The second thing that got a lot of traction is pre-training, specifically the recipe of pre-training.
요즘 사람들이 RL을 하는
방식은 어쩌면 사전학습이
I think the way people do RL now is maybe undoing the conceptual imprint of pre-training.
남긴 개념적 각인을
되돌리고 있는 것 같아요.
그런데 사전학습에는
이런 특성이 있었어요.
But pre-training had this property.
사전학습을 더 하면 모델이 거의
모든 면에서 고르게 좋아져요.
You do more pre-training and the model gets better at everything, more or less uniformly.
일반 AI요.
General AI.
사전학습이 AGI를 만들어줘요.
Pre-training gives AGI.
그런데 AGI와 사전학습에
일어난 일은 어떤
But the thing that happened with AGI and pre-training is that in some sense they overshot the target.
의미에서 목표를 넘어서 쏴버린 거예요.
'AGI'라는 용어를, 특히
사전학습 맥락에서 생각해보면
If you think about the term "AGI", especially in the context of pre-training, you will realize that a human being is not an AGI.
인간은 AGI가 아니라는
걸 알게 되실 거예요.
네, 분명 기초 능력은 있지만
인간에겐 방대한 지식이 빠져 있어요.
Yes, there is definitely a foundation of skills, but a human being lacks a huge amount of knowledge.
대신 우리는 지속 학습에 의존하죠.
Instead, we rely on continual learning.
그러니까 "좋아, 우리가 성공해서 안전한
So when you think about, "Okay, so let's suppose that we achieve success and we produce some kind of safe superintelligence."
초지능을 만들어냈다고 하자"라고 하면요.
질문은, 그걸 어떻게 정의하느냐예요.
The question is, how do you define it?
지속 학습 곡선의 어느 지점에 있을까요?
Where on the curve of continual learning is it going to be?
저는 아주 의욕 넘치는 15살짜리
초지능을 만들어낸 거예요.
I produce a superintelligent 15-year-old that's very eager to go.
아는 건 별로 없지만 훌륭한
학생이고 의욕이 넘치죠.
They don't know very much at all, a great student, very eager.
"가서 프로그래머가 돼라, 가서
의사가 돼라, 가서 배워라."
You go and be a programmer, you go and be a doctor, go and learn.
그러니 배포 자체가 일종의 시행착오
학습 기간을 포함하는 셈이죠.
So you could imagine that the deployment itself will involve some kind of a learning trial-and-error period.
완성품을 딱 내놓는 게
아니라 하나의 과정인 거예요.
It's a process, as opposed to you dropping the finished thing.
그렇군요.
I see.
그러니까 지금 말씀하시는
초지능은 경제의 모든
You're suggesting that the thing you're pointing out with superintelligence is not some finished mind which knows how to do every single job in the economy.
일을 할 줄 아는 완성된
정신이 아니라는 거네요.
예를 들어 오픈AI 헌장에서
AGI를 정의하는 방식은, 인간이
Because the way, say, the original OpenAI charter or whatever defines AGI is like, it can do every single job, every single thing a human can do.
할 수 있는 모든 일을 다 할
수 있어야 한다는 거잖아요.
대신 모든 일을 배울 수 있는 정신을
You're proposing instead a mind which can learn to do every single job, and that is superintelligence.
제안하시는 거고, 그게
바로 초지능이고요.
맞아요.
Yes.
그런데 일단 학습
알고리즘이 갖춰지면 사람이
But once you have the learning algorithm, it gets deployed into the world the same way a human laborer might join an organization.
조직에 들어가듯 세상에 배포되는 거예요.
정확해요.
Exactly.
이 둘 중 하나가 일어날 것 같은데
어쩌면 둘 다 아닐 수도 있고요.
It seems like one of these two things might happen, maybe neither of these happens.
하나는, 이 초효율적인 학습
알고리즘이 ML 연구라는 작업에서
One, this super-efficient learning algorithm becomes superhuman, becomes as good as you and potentially even better, at the task of ML research.
초인적이 돼서 당신만큼, 어쩌면
더 뛰어나질 수 있다는 거예요.
그 결과 알고리즘 자체가 점점
더 초인적으로 되어가는 거고요.
As a result the algorithm itself becomes more and more superhuman.
다른 하나는, 설령 그런 일이
일어나지 않더라도—이건 명시적으로
The other is, even if that doesn't happen, if you have a single model—this is explicitly your vision—where instances of a model which are deployed through the economy doing different jobs, learning how to do those jobs, continually learning on the job, picking up all the skills that any human could pick up, but picking them all up at the same time, and then amalgamating their learnings, you basically have a model which functionally becomes superintelligent even without any sort of recursive self-improvement in software.
당신의 비전인데요—단일 모델이
있어서, 그 모델의 인스턴스들이
경제 전반에 배포되어 서로 다른
일을 하고, 그 일을 하는 법을
배우고, 일을 하면서 지속 학습을
하고, 인간이 습득할 수 있는
모든 기술을 습득하는데, 그것도
전부 동시에 습득한 다음 그
학습 결과들을 하나로 합친다면,
소프트웨어 차원의 재귀적 자기
개선 없이도 사실상 초지능이
되는 모델을 갖게 되는 거죠.
왜냐하면 이제 경제의 모든 일을
다 할 수 있는 모델 하나가
Because you now have one model that can do every single job in the economy and humans can't merge our minds in the same way.
생기는 거고, 인간은 그런 식으로
정신을 합칠 수 없으니까요.
그럼 광범위한 배포로부터 일종의 지능
폭발이 일어날 거라고 보시나요?
So do you expect some sort of intelligence explosion from broad deployment?
저는 우리가 빠른 경제 성장을
이루게 될 가능성이 높다고 봐요.
I think that it is likely that we will have rapid economic growth.
광범위한 배포와
관련해서는, 서로 상충하는
I think with broad deployment, there are two arguments you could make which are conflicting.
주장 두 가지를 할 수 있다고 생각해요.
하나는, 실제로 AI가 빠르게
뭔가를 배울 수 있는 지점에
One is that once indeed you get to a point where you have an AI that can learn to do things quickly and you have many of them, then there will be a strong force to deploy them in the economy unless there will be some kind of a regulation that stops it, which by the way there might be.
도달하고 그런 AI가 많이
있게 되면, 어떤 규제가 막지
않는 한 그것들을 경제에
배치하려는 강한 힘이 작용할 거라는
거예요. 그런데 그런 규제가
실제로 있을 수도 있고요.
하지만 한동안 매우 빠른 경제
성장이 일어난다는 아이디어,
But the idea of very rapid economic growth for some time, I think it’s very possible from broad deployment.
그건 광범위한 배포로부터
충분히 가능하다고 봐요.
문제는 그게 얼마나
빠를 것이냐는 거고요.
The question is how rapid it's going to be.
이건 알기 어렵다고
생각하는데요, 한편으로는
I think this is hard to know because on the one hand you have this very efficient worker.
이렇게 매우 효율적인
노동자가 있는 거잖아요.
다른 한편으로는 세상은 정말
크고 처리할 일이 정말
On the other hand, the world is just really big and there's a lot of stuff, and that stuff moves at a different speed.
많은데, 그 일은 또
다른 속도로 움직이고요.
그런데 또 다른
한편으로는, 이제 AI가…
But then on the other hand, now the AI could…
그래서 저는 매우 빠른 경제
성장이 가능하다고 봐요.
So I think very rapid economic growth is possible.
온갖 일들이 다 벌어질 거예요.
나라마다 규칙이 다르고, 더
We will see all kinds of things like different countries with different rules and the ones which have the friendlier rules, the economic growth will be faster.
우호적인 규칙을 가진 나라일수록
경제 성장이 더 빠를 거고요.
예측하기 어렵죠.
Hard to predict.
제가 보기엔 이건 아주
위태로운 상황인 것 같아요.
It seems to me that this is a very precarious situation to be in.
극한으로 가면, 이게 가능해야
한다는 건 이미 알고 있는 거죠.
In the limit, we know that this should be possible.
학습 면에서 인간만큼
뛰어나면서도, 인간은 할 수 없는
If you have something that is as good as a human at learning, but which can merge its brains—merge different instances in a way that humans can't merge—already, this seems like a thing that should physically be possible.
방식으로 서로 다른 인스턴스들의
뇌를 합칠 수 있는 무언가가
있다면, 이건 이미 물리적으로
가능해야 하는 일처럼 보여요.
인간도 가능하고, 디지털
컴퓨터도 가능하잖아요.
Humans are possible, digital computers are possible.
그 둘을 합치기만 하면 이런
존재가 만들어지는 거고요.
You just need both of those combined to produce this thing.
이런 존재는 또한 극도로
강력할 것 같기도 하고요.
It also seems this kind of thing is extremely powerful.
경제 성장이라는 게 그걸
표현하는 한 방식이죠.
Economic growth is one way to put it.
다이슨 스피어는 엄청난
경제 성장이잖아요.
A Dyson sphere is a lot of economic growth.
하지만 또 다른 표현
방식은, 어쩌면 아주 짧은
But another way to put it is that you will have, in potentially a very short period of time...
시간 안에 이런 걸 갖게
될 거라는 거예요…
SSI에서 사람을 채용하면, 아마 6개월
You hire people at SSI, and in six months, they're net productive, probably.
안에는 순수하게 생산적인
인력이 되잖아요.
인간은 정말 빠르게 배우는데, 이것은
A human learns really fast, and this thing is becoming smarter and smarter very fast.
점점 더 빠르게 더 똑똑해지고 있고요.
그 일이 잘 풀리게 하려면
어떻게 해야 한다고 보시나요?
How do you think about making that go well?
SSI가 그걸 잘 해낼 수 있는
위치에 있는 이유는 뭔가요?
Why is SSI positioned to do that well?
결국 제가 여쭙고 싶은 건, 거기서
SSI의 계획이 무엇이냐는 거예요.
What is SSI's plan there, is basically what I'm trying to ask.
제 생각이 달라져 온 방식 중
하나는, 이제 AI를 점진적으로,
One of the ways in which my thinking has been changing is that I now place more importance on AI being deployed incrementally and in advance.
그리고 미리 배포하는 데
더 무게를 둔다는 거예요.
AI에 관해 정말 어려운 점
하나는, 아직 존재하지 않는
One very difficult thing about AI is that we are talking about systems that don't yet exist and it's hard to imagine them.
시스템 얘기를 하고 있다 보니
상상하기가 어렵다는 거예요.
벌어지고 있는 일 중
하나는, 실제로는 AGI를
I think that one of the things that's happening is that in practice, it's very hard to feel the AGI.
체감하기가 정말 어렵다는
거라고 생각해요.
AGI를 체감하기는 정말 어려워요.
It's very hard to feel the AGI.
그것에 대해 이야기할 순
있지만, 나이 들고 노쇠해졌을
We can talk about it, but imagine having a conversation about how it is like to be old when you're old and frail.
때 늙는다는 게 어떤 건지
대화하는 상상을 해보세요.
대화를 나눌 수도, 상상해보려
할 수도 있지만 그냥
You can have a conversation, you can try to imagine it, but it's just hard, and you come back to reality where that's not the case.
어렵고, 결국 그렇지 않은
현실로 돌아오게 되죠.
AGI와 그 미래 힘을
둘러싼 문제들 상당수는, 그걸
I think that a lot of the issues around AGI and its future power stem from the fact that it's very difficult to imagine.
상상하기가 너무 어렵다는
데서 비롯된다고 봐요.
미래의 AI는 다를 거예요.
Future AI is going to be different.
강력할 거고요.
It's going to be powerful.
실제로, 그 문제 전체가—AI와
AGI의 문제란 대체 뭘까요?
Indeed, the whole problem, what is the problem of AI and AGI?
그 문제 전체가 바로 힘이에요.
The whole problem is the power.
그 힘이 정말로 커지면,
무슨 일이 벌어질까요?
When the power is really big, what's going to happen?
지난 1년간 제 생각이 바뀐
것 중 하나는—그리고 그
One of the ways in which I've changed my mind over the past year—and that change of mind, I'll hedge a little bit, may back-propagate into the plans of our company—is that if it's hard to imagine, what do you do?
변화는, 조심스럽게 말하자면
저희 회사의 계획에도 역전파될
수 있는데—상상하기 어렵다면
어떻게 해야 하느냐는 거예요.
그걸 직접 보여줘야 해요.
You’ve got to be showing the thing.
저는 AI를 연구하는 사람들
대부분도 그걸 상상하지
I maintain that most people who work on AI also can't imagine it because it's too different from what people see on a day-to-day basis.
못한다고 봐요, 일상에서
보는 것과 너무 다르니까요.
제가 확신하는 건, 이런 일이
일어날 거라고 예측한다는 거예요.
I do maintain, here's something which I predict will happen.
이건 예측이에요.
This is a prediction.
AI가 더 강력해질수록, 사람들이
행동을 바꿀 거라고 봐요.
I maintain that as AI becomes more powerful, people will change their behaviors.
지금은 일어나지 않는 온갖 전례
없는 일들을 보게 될 거예요.
We will see all kinds of unprecedented things which are not happening right now.
몇 가지 예를 들어볼게요.
I’ll give some examples.
좋든 나쁘든, 앞으로 일어날
일에서 프론티어 기업들이 아주
I think for better or worse, the frontier companies will play a very important role in what happens, as will the government.
중요한 역할을 할 거라고
생각해요. 정부도 마찬가지고요.
앞으로 보게 될 거라고
생각하는 것 중 하나는, 이미
The kind of things that I think you'll see, which you see the beginnings of, are companies that are fierce competitors starting to collaborate on AI safety.
시작되는 조짐이 보이는데,
치열하게 경쟁하던 기업들이
AI 안전 문제에서는 협력하기
시작하는 모습이에요.
오픈AI와 앤트로픽이
작은 첫걸음을 떼는 걸
You may have seen OpenAI and Anthropic doing a first small step, but that did not exist.
보셨을 텐데, 예전에는
그런 게 존재하지 않았죠.
그건 제가 한 3년 전쯤
어느 강연에서 이런
That's something which I predicted in one of my talks about three years ago, that such a thing will happen.
일이 일어날 거라고 예측했던 부분이에요.
그리고 저는, AI가 계속
더 강력해지고 그 강력함이
I also maintain that as AI continues to become more powerful, more visibly powerful, there will also be a desire from governments and the public to do something.
눈에 더 잘 보이게 될수록,
정부와 대중 쪽에서도 뭔가
조치를 취하고 싶어 하는
욕구가 생길 거라고 봐요.
AI를 직접 보여주는 것, 그 자체가
아주 중요한 힘이라고 생각해요.
I think this is a very important force, of showing the AI.
그게 첫 번째예요.
That's number one.
두 번째는, 자, AI가
만들어지고 있잖아요.
Number two, okay, so the AI is being built.
그럼 뭘 해야 할까요?
What needs to be done?
제가 일어날 거라고 보는 것 중 하나는,
지금 AI를 만드는 사람들한테는
One thing that I maintain that will happen is that right now, people who are working on AI, I maintain that the AI doesn't feel powerful because of its mistakes.
AI가 실수를 저지르기 때문에
강력하게 느껴지지 않는다는 거예요.
하지만 어느 시점이 되면 AI가 실제로
I do think that at some point the AI will start to feel powerful actually.
강력하게 느껴지기
시작할 거라고 생각해요.
그런 일이 일어나면,
모든 AI 기업이 안전에
I think when that happens, we will see a big change in the way all AI companies approach safety.
접근하는 방식에서 큰
변화가 나타날 거라고 봐요.
훨씬 더 편집증적이 될 거예요.
They'll become much more paranoid.
이건 앞으로 실제로 일어나는 걸 보게
I say this as a prediction that we will see happen.
될 거라는 예측으로 드리는 말씀이에요.
제 말이 맞는지는 두고 봐야겠죠.
We'll see if I'm right.
하지만 AI가 더
강력해지는 걸 직접 보게
But I think this is something that will happen because they will see the AI becoming more powerful.
될 테니, 이런 일이
일어날 거라고 생각해요.
지금 벌어지고 있는 모든 일은,
제가 보기엔, 사람들이 오늘날의
Everything that's happening right now, I maintain, is because people look at today's AI and it's hard to imagine the future AI.
AI를 보면서 미래의 AI는 상상하기
어려워하기 때문이라고 생각해요.
세 번째로 일어나야 할 일이 있어요.
There is a third thing which needs to happen.
저희 회사에 대해 물어보셔서
그런데, SSI 관점에서만이
I'm talking about it in broader terms, not just from the perspective of SSI because you asked me about our company.
아니라 더 넓은 의미에서
말씀드리는 거예요.
질문은, 기업들이 무엇을 만들겠다는
포부를 가져야 하느냐는 거예요.
The question is, what should the companies aspire to build?
무엇을 만들고자 해야 할까요?
What should they aspire to build?
모두가 매달려 온 하나의 큰 아이디어가
There has been one big idea that everyone has been locked into, which is the self-improving AI.
있었는데, 바로 자기 개선형 AI예요.
왜 그렇게 됐을까요?
Why did it happen?
아이디어보다 기업 수가
더 많기 때문이에요.
Because there are fewer ideas than companies.
하지만 저는 그보다 더
나은, 만들 만한 것이 있다고
But I maintain that there is something that's better to build, and I think that everyone will want that.
생각하고, 모두가 그걸
원하게 될 거라고 봐요.
그건 바로 지각 있는 생명을 특히 소중히
It's the AI that's robustly aligned to care about sentient life specifically.
여기도록 강건하게 정렬된 AI예요.
지각 있는 생명을 소중히 여기는
AI를 만드는 게, 인간의
I think in particular, there's a case to be made that it will be easier to build an AI that cares about sentient life than an AI that cares about human life alone, because the AI itself will be sentient.
생명만 소중히 여기는 AI를
만드는 것보다 오히려 더 쉬울
수 있다고 봐요. AI 자신도
지각이 있는 존재일 테니까요.
거울 뉴런이나, 인간이 동물에게
느끼는 공감 같은 걸 생각해보면—
And if you think about things like mirror neurons and human empathy for animals, which you might argue it's not big enough, but it exists.
충분히 크지 않다고 반박할 수도
있지만, 분명히 존재하긴 하죠.
우리가 타인을 모델링할 때도 자신을
모델링하는 것과 같은 회로를 쓰기
I think it's an emergent property from the fact that we model others with the same circuit that we use to model ourselves, because that's the most efficient thing to do.
때문에 나타나는 창발적 속성이라고
봐요. 그게 가장 효율적인 방식이니까요.
그러니 AI가 지각 있는 존재들을
소중히 여기도록 만들었다 해도— 정렬
So even if you got an AI to care about sentient beings—and it's not actually clear to me that that's what you should try to do if you solved alignment—it would still be the case that most sentient beings will be AIs.
문제를 풀었을 때 그게 정말 추구해야
할 목표인지는 사실 저도 확신이
없는데— 그래도 결국 대부분의 지각
있는 존재는 AI가 될 거예요.
AI는 수조 개, 결국엔
수천조 개에 이를 테니까요.
There will be trillions, eventually quadrillions, of AIs.
인간은 지각 있는 존재 중 아주
작은 일부에 불과할 거고요.
Humans will be a very small fraction of sentient beings.
그러니 목표가 이 미래
문명에 대한 인간의 통제 같은
So it's not clear to me if the goal is some kind of human control over this future civilization, that this is the best criterion.
거라면, 이게 최선의
기준인지는 저도 확신이 없어요.
맞아요.
It's true.
최선의 기준이 아닐 수도 있고요.
It's possible it's not the best criterion.
두 가지를 말씀드릴게요.
I'll say two things.
첫째, 지각 있는 생명을 소중히 여기라는
Number one, care for sentient life, I think there is merit to it.
것— 거기엔 나름의 가치가 있다고 봐요.
고려해볼 만한 가치가 있어요.
It should be considered.
이런 상황에 놓였을 때
기업들이 참고할 수 있는 짧은
I think it would be helpful if there was some kind of short list of ideas that the companies, when they are in this situation, could use.
아이디어 목록 같은 게
있으면 도움이 될 것 같아요.
그게 둘째고요.
That’s number two.
셋째, 가장 강력한 초지능의 힘을
어떻게든 제한할 수 있다면 실질적으로
Number three, I think it would be really materially helpful if the power of the most powerful superintelligence was somehow capped because it would address a lot of these concerns.
정말 큰 도움이 될 거예요. 이런
우려들 상당수를 해소해줄 테니까요.
어떻게 그렇게 할지는 저도 잘
모르겠지만, 정말 정말 강력한
The question of how to do it, I'm not sure, but I think that would be materially helpful when you're talking about really, really powerful systems.
시스템을 이야기할 땐 실질적으로
도움이 될 거라고 봐요.
정렬 논의를 계속 이어가기 전에, 그
Before we continue the alignment discussion, I want to double-click on that.
부분을 좀 더 파고들어보고 싶은데요.
그 위쪽으로는 대체 얼마나
여지가 있는 걸까요?
How much room is there at the top?
초지능을 어떻게 이해하고 계신가요?
How do you think about superintelligence?
이 학습 효율성이라는 개념으로
보면, 초지능은 그저 새로운
Do you think, using this learning efficiency idea, maybe it is just extremely fast at learning new skills or new knowledge?
기술이나 지식을 극도로 빠르게
배우는 존재일 뿐일까요?
아니면 그냥 더 큰 전략
풀을 갖고 있는 걸까요?
Does it just have a bigger pool of strategies?
중심에 하나로 응집된, 더 강력하고
더 큰 '그것'이 있는 걸까요?
Is there a single cohesive "it" in the center that's more powerful or bigger?
그렇다면 이게 나머지 인류 문명에 비해
신 같은 존재로 느껴질까요, 아니면
If so, do you imagine that this will be sort of godlike in comparison to the rest of human civilization, or does it just feel like another agent, or another cluster of agents?
그냥 또 다른 에이전트나 에이전트들의
또 다른 집합체처럼 느껴질까요?
이건 사람마다 직관이 다른 영역이에요.
This is an area where different people have different intuitions.
정말 강력할 게 틀림없다고 생각해요.
I think it will be very powerful, for sure.
제 생각에 가장 가능성이 높은 건, 그런
What I think is most likely to happen is that there will be multiple such AIs being created roughly at the same time.
AI가 여럿이 거의
동시에 만들어지는 거예요.
클러스터가 충분히 크다면
— 말 그대로 대륙 크기
I think that if the cluster is big enough—like if the cluster is literally continent-sized—that thing could be really powerful, indeed.
클러스터라면 — 그건 정말
강력할 수 있다고 생각해요.
말 그대로 대륙 크기
클러스터를 갖게 된다면,
If you literally have a continent-sized cluster, those AIs can be very powerful.
그 AI들은 정말 강력해질 수 있어요.
제가 말씀드릴 수 있는 건,
극도로 강력한 AI, 정말
All I can tell you is that if you're talking about extremely powerful AIs, truly dramatically powerful, it would be nice if they could be restrained in some ways or if there were some kind of agreement or something.
극적으로 강력한 AI를 얘기하는
거라면, 어떤 식으로든
제약이 있거나 일종의 합의 같은
게 있으면 좋겠다는 거예요.
초지능의 우려는 뭔가요?
What is the concern of superintelligence?
그 우려를 설명하는 한
가지 방법은 뭘까요?
What is one way to explain the concern?
충분히 강력한 시스템을,
정말로 충분히 강력한 시스템을
If you imagine a system that is sufficiently powerful, really sufficiently powerful—and you could say you need to do something sensible like care for sentient life in a very single-minded way—we might not like the results.
상상해보면 — 그리고 지각
있는 생명을 소중히 여기는
것처럼 뭔가 합리적인 일을
아주 외곬으로 하라고 시킨다면
— 우리가 그 결과를 마음에
들어하지 않을 수도 있어요.
정말로 그게 핵심이에요.
That's really what it is.
그런데 어쩌면 답은,
일반적인 의미의 RL
Maybe, by the way, the answer is that you do not build an RL agent in the usual sense.
에이전트를 만들지 않는
거일 수도 있어요.
몇 가지를 짚어볼게요.
I'll point several things out.
저는 인간이 반(半) RL
에이전트라고 생각해요.
I think human beings are semi-RL agents.
보상을 좇다가, 감정이든
뭐든 그게 우리를 그 보상에
We pursue a reward, and then the emotions or whatever make us tire out of the reward and we pursue a different reward.
지치게 만들고, 그러면
다른 보상을 좇게 되죠.
시장은 아주 근시안적인
종류의 에이전트예요.
The market is a very short-sighted kind of agent.
진화도 마찬가지예요.
Evolution is the same.
진화는 어떤 면에서는 아주 똑똑하지만,
다른 면에서는 아주 멍청해요.
Evolution is very intelligent in some ways, but very dumb in other ways.
정부는 세 부분 사이의
끝나지 않는 싸움으로
The government has been designed to be a never-ending fight between three parts, which has an effect.
설계돼 있고, 그게 어떤 효과를 내죠.
그러니까 저는 이런 것들을 생각해요.
So I think things like this.
이 논의를 어렵게 만드는 또 다른
건, 우리가 존재하지 않는,
Another thing that makes this discussion difficult is that we are talking about systems that don't exist, that we don't know how to build.
어떻게 만드는지도 모르는 시스템을
얘기하고 있다는 거예요.
그게 또 다른 이유고,
사실 그게 제 믿음이에요.
That’s the other thing and that’s actually my belief.
지금 사람들이 하고 있는
건 어느 정도까지는
I think what people are doing right now will go some distance and then peter out.
가다가 결국 사그라들 거라고 생각해요.
계속 개선되긴 하겠지만, 그게
'그것'은 아닐 거예요.
It will continue to improve, but it will also not be "it".
'그것'을 우리는 어떻게
만드는지 모르고, 많은 게
The "It" we don't know how to build, and a lot hinges on understanding reliable generalization.
신뢰할 수 있는 일반화를
이해하는 데 달려 있어요.
한 가지 더 말씀드릴게요.
I’ll say another thing.
정렬을 어렵게 만드는 원인
중 하나로 꼽을 수 있는
One of the things that you could say about what causes alignment to be difficult is that your ability to learn human values is fragile.
건, 인간의 가치를 학습하는
능력이 취약하다는 거예요.
그럼 그것들을 최적화하는
능력도 취약해지는 거죠.
Then your ability to optimize them is fragile.
실제로는 그것들을 최적화하는
법을 배우긴 해요.
You actually learn to optimize them.
그리고 이렇게 말할 수 있지
않을까요, "이것들 전부
And can't you say, "Are these not all instances of unreliable generalization?"
신뢰할 수 없는 일반화의
사례 아닌가?"라고요?
그런데 왜 인간은 훨씬 더
일반화를 잘하는 것처럼 보일까요?
Why is it that human beings appear to generalize so much better?
일반화가 훨씬 더 뛰어나다면 어떨까요?
What if generalization was much better?
그렇다면 무슨 일이 벌어질까요?
What would happen in this case?
그 효과는 어떤 걸까요?
What would be the effect?
하지만 이 질문들엔
지금으로선 답할 수가 없어요.
But those questions are right now still unanswerable.
AI가 잘 풀린다는 게 어떤
모습일지, 어떻게 생각해야 할까요?
How does one think about what AI going well looks like?
AI가 어떻게 진화할지
그림을 그려보셨잖아요.
You've scoped out how AI might evolve.
지속 학습을 하는
에이전트들이 생길 거고요.
We'll have these sort of continual learning agents.
AI는 아주 강력해질 거고요.
AI will be very powerful.
어쩌면 서로 다른 AI들이
여럿 존재하겠죠.
Maybe there will be many different AIs.
대륙 크기의 컴퓨트를
가진 지능들이 곳곳에
How do you think about lots of continent-sized compute intelligences going around?
돌아다니는 상황, 어떻게 생각하세요?
그게 얼마나 위험할까요?
How dangerous is that?
그 위험을 어떻게 줄일 수 있을까요?
How do we make that less dangerous?
그리고 어딘가엔 정렬되지 않은
AI들과 악의적인 행위자들이 있을
And how do we do that in a way that protects an equilibrium where there might be misaligned AIs out there and bad actors out there?
수 있는 균형을 지키면서, 그걸
어떻게 해낼 수 있을까요?
"지각 있는 생명을
소중히 여기는 AI"를
Here’s one reason why I liked "AI that cares for sentient life".
제가 좋아하는 이유 중
하나가 바로 이거예요.
이게 좋은 건지 나쁜
건지는 논쟁할 수 있어요.
We can debate on whether it's good or bad.
하지만 이 극적인 시스템들
중 처음 등장하는 N개가
But if the first N of these dramatic systems do care for, love, humanity or something, care for sentient life, obviously this also needs to be achieved.
인류를 아끼고 사랑한다면,
그러니까 지각 있는 생명을
소중히 여긴다면, 물론 이것
역시 이뤄내야만 해요.
이건 이뤄내야만 해요.
This needs to be achieved.
그러니까 처음 N개의
시스템이 이걸 이뤄낸다면,
So if this is achieved by the first N of those systems, then I can see it go well, at least for quite some time.
적어도 한동안은 잘
흘러갈 수 있다고 봐요.
그다음엔 장기적으로 어떻게
될 것인가 하는 질문이 남죠.
Then there is the question of what happens in the long run.
장기적인 균형 상태는
어떻게 이룰 수 있을까요?
How do you achieve a long-run equilibrium?
그 지점에도 답은 있다고 생각해요.
I think that there, there is an answer as well.
저는 이 답이 마음에 들지 않지만,
그래도 고려는 해봐야 해요.
I don't like this answer, but it needs to be considered.
장기적으로 보면 이렇게 말할
수도 있어요. "좋아요,
In the long run, you might say, "Okay, if you have a world where powerful AIs exist, in the short term, you could say you have universal high income.
강력한 AI가 존재하는
세상이라면, 단기적으로는
보편적 고소득을 갖게
됐다고 할 수 있죠."
"보편적 고소득이 있고, 우리 모두
잘 지내고 있어요"라고 말이죠.
You have universal high income and we're all doing well."
그런데 불교에서는 뭐라고 하죠?
But what do the Buddhists say?
"변화만이 유일한 상수다."
"Change is the only constant."
모든 건 변해요.
Things change.
정부나 정치 구조 같은
게 있는데, 그것도
There is some kind of government, political structure thing, and it changes because these things have a shelf life.
변하죠. 이런 것들은
유효기간이 있으니까요.
새로운 정부 형태가 등장해서 한동안
Some new government thing comes up and it functions, and then after some time it stops functioning.
작동하다가, 시간이
지나면 작동을 멈추죠.
우리는 그런 일이 늘
일어나는 걸 봐왔어요.
That's something that we see happening all the time.
그래서 저는 장기적인 균형
상태에 대해, 모든 사람이
So I think for the long-run equilibrium, one approach is that you could say maybe every person will have an AI that will do their bidding, and that's good.
자기 대신 일해줄 AI를
하나씩 갖게 될 거고, 그건
좋은 일이라고 말하는 게 한
가지 접근이라고 생각해요.
그게 무한정 유지될 수
있다면, 맞는 말이에요.
If that could be maintained indefinitely, that's true.
그런데 문제는, 그럼 그 AI가
나가서 그 사람 대신 돈을 벌고,
But the downside with that is then the AI goes and earns money for the person and advocates for their needs in the political sphere, and maybe then writes a little report saying, "Okay, here's what I've done, here's the situation," and the person says, "Great, keep it up."
정치 영역에서 그 사람의 필요를
대변하고, 그러고 나서 아마 짧은
보고서 하나를 써서 "자, 제가 한
일은 이렇고 상황은 이렇습니다"라고
하면, 그 사람은 "좋아,
계속해"라고 말한다는 거예요.
하지만 그 사람은 더 이상
참여자가 아니게 되죠.
But the person is no longer a participant.
그럼 그건 불안정한 위치에
있는 거라고 할 수 있어요.
Then you can say that's a precarious place to be in.
미리 말씀드리자면,
저는 이 해법이 마음에
I'm going to preface by saying I don't like this solution, but it is a solution.
들지 않지만, 그래도
하나의 해법이긴 해요.
그 해법은 사람들이 일종의 뉴럴링크++를
The solution is if people become part-AI with some kind of Neuralink++.
통해 부분적으로 AI가 되는 거예요.
그 결과로 일어나는 일은, AI가
뭔가를 이해하면 우리도 그걸
Because what will happen as a result is that now the AI understands something, and we understand it too, because now the understanding is transmitted wholesale.
이해하게 된다는 거예요. 이해
자체가 통째로 전달되니까요.
그래서 이제 AI가 어떤 상황에 놓이면,
So now if the AI is in some situation, you are involved in that situation yourself fully.
우리도 그 상황에 완전히
관여하게 되는 거죠.
저는 이게 균형 상태에
대한 답이라고 생각해요.
I think this is the answer to the equilibrium.
저는 수백만 년, 많은 경우
수십억 년 전 완전히 다른 환경에서
I wonder if the fact that emotions which were developed millions—or in many cases, billions—of years ago in a totally different environment are still guiding our actions so strongly is an example of alignment success.
발달한 감정이 지금도 우리
행동을 이렇게 강하게 이끌고
있다는 사실 자체가 정렬 성공의
한 사례가 아닐까 싶어요.
좀 더 풀어서 말씀드리면—
이걸 가치 함수라고 불러야
To spell out what I mean—I don’t know whether it’s more accurate to call it a value function or reward function—but the brainstem has a directive where it's saying, "Mate with somebody who's more successful."
할지 보상 함수라고 불러야
할지는 모르겠지만— 뇌간에는
"더 성공한 사람과
짝짓기하라"는 지침이 있어요.
대뇌 피질은 현대적 맥락에서 성공이
뭘 의미하는지를 이해하는 부분이에요.
The cortex is the part that understands what success means in the modern context.
그런데 뇌간은 대뇌 피질을
정렬시켜서 이렇게 말할 수 있어요.
But the brainstem is able to align the cortex and say, "However you recognize success to be—and I’m not smart enough to understand what that is— you're still going to pursue this directive."
"네가 성공을 뭐라고 인식하든—
그게 뭔지 이해할 만큼 나는
똑똑하지 않지만— 그래도 너는 이
지침을 계속 추구하게 될 거야."
저는 더 일반적인
논점이 있다고 생각해요.
I think there's a more general point.
저는 진화가 고차원적인 욕구를 어떻게
I think it's actually really mysterious how evolution encodes high-level desires.
부호화하는지가 사실 정말
신비롭다고 생각해요.
냄새는 화학물질이니까, 좋은 냄새
나는 음식에 대한 욕구를 진화가
It's pretty easy to understand how evolution would endow us with the desire for food that smells good because smell is a chemical, so just pursue that chemical.
심어줬다는 건 이해하기 쉬워요. 그냥
그 화학물질을 쫓으면 되니까요.
진화가 그런 일을 했다는
건 아주 쉽게 상상이 가요.
It's very easy to imagine evolution doing that thing.
그런데 진화는 이런 다양한 사회적
욕구들도 우리에게 심어줬어요.
But evolution also has endowed us with all these social desires.
우리는 사회에서 긍정적으로
비춰지는 걸 정말 신경 쓰죠.
We really care about being seen positively by society.
평판이 좋은 상태를 유지하는
것도 신경 쓰고요.
We care about being in good standing.
우리가 가진 이런 사회적 직관들, 저는
All these social intuitions that we have, I feel strongly that they're baked in.
이게 타고난 거라고 강하게 느껴요.
진화가 어떻게 그걸
해냈는지는 모르겠어요.
I don't know how evolution did it because it's a high-level concept that's represented in the brain.
뇌 안에서 표상되는
고차원적 개념이니까요.
어떤 사회적인 것을 신경 쓴다고 해봐요.
Let’s say you care about some social thing, it's not a low-level signal like smell.
그건 냄새 같은 저수준 신호가 아니에요.
그걸 감지하는 센서 같은
게 있는 것도 아니고요.
It's not something for which there is a sensor.
뇌가 사회적으로 무슨 일이
벌어지는지 이해하려면, 수많은
The brain needs to do a lot of processing to piece together lots of bits of information to understand what's going on socially.
정보 조각을 짜맞추는 처리
과정을 많이 거쳐야 해요.
그런데 진화는 어떻게든 "바로 그걸
신경 써야 해"라고 말한 거예요.
Somehow evolution said, "That's what you should care about."
대체 어떻게 그렇게 한 걸까요?
How did it do it?
그것도 빠르게 해냈고요.
It did it quickly, too.
우리가 신경 쓰는 이런 정교한 사회적인
All these sophisticated social things that we care about, I think they evolved pretty recently.
것들은, 꽤 최근에 진화했다고 생각해요.
진화는 이런 고차원적 욕구를
아무렇지도 않게 하드코딩해낸 거예요.
Evolution had an easy time hard-coding this high-level desire.
어떻게 그렇게 했는지에 대한
괜찮은 가설을, 저는 모르겠어요.
I'm unaware of a good hypothesis for how it's done.
이런저런 아이디어를 굴려봤지만,
어느 것도 만족스럽지 않았어요.
I had some ideas I was kicking around, but none of them are satisfying.
특히 인상적인 지점은
이거예요. 만약 이게 살아가면서
What's especially impressive is it was desire that you learned in your lifetime, it makes sense because your brain is intelligent.
학습한 욕구였다면, 뇌가
똑똑하니까 말이 되죠.
똑똑한 욕구를 학습할 수 있다는
것 자체는 말이 되는 거예요.
It makes sense why you would be able to learn intelligent desires.
그게 하려던 말은 아니었을
수도 있지만, 이렇게
Maybe this is not your point, but one way to understand it is that the desire is built into the genome, and the genome is not intelligent.
이해하는 방법도 있어요.
욕구는 유전체 안에 새겨져
있는데, 유전체 자체는
똑똑하지 않다는 거죠.
그런데 어떻게든 이 특성을
기술할 수 있다는 거예요.
But you're somehow able to describe this feature.
그 특성을 어떻게
정의하는지조차 불분명한데,
It's not even clear how you define that feature, and you can build it into the genes.
그걸 유전자에 새겨
넣을 수 있다는 거죠.
본질적으로는요, 아니면
다르게 말해볼게요.
Essentially, or maybe I'll put it differently.
유전체가 쓸 수 있는 도구들을
생각해보면, 유전체는 "좋아,
If you think about the tools that are available to the genome, it says, "Okay, here's a recipe for building a brain."
뇌를 만드는 레시피는
이거야"라고 말하는 셈이에요.
이렇게 말할 수도 있겠죠.
"여기 도파민 뉴런을
You could say, "Here is a recipe for connecting the dopamine neurons to the smell sensor."
냄새 센서에 연결하는
레시피가 있어"라고요.
그리고 냄새가 어떤 좋은 냄새라면,
그걸 먹고 싶어지는 거죠.
And if the smell is a certain kind of good smell, you want to eat that.
게놈이 그렇게 하는 건 상상이 가요.
I could imagine the genome doing that.
제가 주장하는 건 그건
상상하기 더 어렵다는 거예요.
I'm claiming that it is harder to imagine.
게놈이 '너의 뇌 전체, 뇌의
상당 부분이 수행하는 어떤 복잡한
It's harder to imagine the genome saying you should care about some complicated computation that your entire brain, a big chunk of your brain, does.
계산을 신경 써야 한다'고 말하는
건 상상하기 더 어렵다는 거죠.
제가 주장하는 건 그게 다예요.
That's all I'm claiming.
그게 어떻게 이뤄질 수 있는지에 대한
추측 하나는 말씀드릴 수 있어요.
I can tell you a speculation of how it could be done.
추측 하나를 제시해 보고, 그 추측이
왜 아마 틀렸는지 설명해 드릴게요.
Let me offer a speculation, and I'll explain why the speculation is probably false.
뇌에는 뇌 영역들이 있죠.
So the brain has brain regions.
우리에겐 대뇌 피질이 있고요.
We have our cortex.
거기엔 그 모든 뇌 영역들이 있어요.
It has all those brain regions.
대뇌 피질은 균일하지만,
그 안의 뇌 영역들과
The cortex is uniform, but the brain regions and the neurons in the cortex kind of speak to their neighbors mostly.
뉴런들은 대체로 이웃끼리만 소통해요.
그게 왜 뇌 영역들이
생기는지를 설명해 주죠.
That explains why you get brain regions.
예를 들어 언어 처리
같은 걸 하려면, 언어를
Because if you want to do some kind of speech processing, all the neurons that do speech need to talk to each other.
담당하는 뉴런들이 서로
소통해야 하니까요.
그리고 뉴런들은 대체로
가까운 이웃하고만 소통할 수
And because neurons can only speak to their nearby neighbors, for the most part, it has to be a region.
있으니, 그게 하나의 영역을
이룰 수밖에 없는 거죠.
그 영역들은 사람마다
대체로 같은 위치에 있고요.
All the regions are mostly located in the same place from person to person.
그러니 어쩌면 진화가 뇌의 어떤 위치를
So maybe evolution hard-coded literally a location on the brain.
말 그대로 하드코딩했을 수도 있어요.
그러니까 "아, 뇌의 이런저런
GPS 좌표에서, 거기가
So it says, "Oh, when the GPS coordinates of the brain such and such, when that fires, that's what you should care about."
발화하면, 그게 네가 신경 써야
할 것이다"라고 말하는 거죠.
어쩌면 그게 진화가
한 일일 수도 있어요,
Maybe that's what evolution did because that would be within the toolkit of evolution.
그건 진화의 도구함 안에
있는 방법이니까요.
네, 그런데 예를 들어 선천적으로
시각장애가 있는 사람들은
Yeah, although there are examples where, for example, people who are born blind have that area of their cortex adopted by another sense.
대뇌 피질의 그 영역을 다른
감각이 차지하는 경우가 있잖아요.
잘은 모르지만, 시각 신호를
필요로 하는 욕구나 보상
I have no idea, but I'd be surprised if the desires or the reward functions which require a visual signal no longer worked for people who have their different areas of their cortex co-opted.
함수가 피질의 다른 영역이
그 자리를 차지한 사람들에게서
더 이상 작동하지 않는다면
저는 놀랄 것 같아요.
예를 들어 시각이 없어지면,
'주변 사람들이 나를
For example, if you no longer have vision, can you still feel the sense that I want people around me to like me and so forth, which usually there are also visual cues for.
좋아했으면 좋겠다' 같은,
보통은 시각적 단서도 함께
따라오는 그런 감정을
여전히 느낄 수 있을까요.
그 말에 전적으로 동의해요.
I fully agree with that.
이 이론에 대한 더 강력한
반론도 있다고 생각해요.
I think there's an even stronger counterargument to this theory.
어릴 때 뇌의 절반이
제거된 사람들이 있는데,
There are people who get half of their brains removed in childhood, and they still have all their brain regions.
그들도 여전히 모든 뇌
영역을 다 갖고 있거든요.
그런데 그게 전부 어떻게든 한쪽 반구로만
옮겨가요, 그건 뇌 영역의 위치가
But they all somehow move to just one hemisphere, which suggests that the brain regions, their location is not fixed and so that theory is not true.
고정된 게 아니라는 뜻이고, 그러니
그 이론은 사실이 아니라는 거죠.
사실이면 멋있었겠지만, 아니에요.
It would have been cool if it was true, but it's not.
그래서 그건 미스터리라고 생각해요.
So I think that's a mystery.
하지만 흥미로운 미스터리죠.
But it's an interesting mystery.
사실은 진화가 어떻게든
우리가 사회적인 것에 아주,
The fact is that somehow evolution was able to endow us to care about social stuff very, very reliably.
아주 안정적으로 신경
쓰도록 만들어냈다는 거예요.
온갖 특이한 정신적 상태나
결핍, 감정적 문제를 가진
Even people who have all kinds of strange mental conditions and deficiencies and emotional problems tend to care about this also.
사람들조차도 이 부분엔
신경을 쓰는 경향이 있어요.
SSI는 무엇을 다르게
하려고 계획하고 있나요?
What is SSI planning on doing differently?
아마 이 시기가 오면 프론티어 기업
중 하나가 되는 게 계획이시겠죠.
Presumably your plan is to be one of the frontier companies when this time arrives.
아마 SSI를 시작하신 것도
"이걸 안전하게 하는 방법을 다른
Presumably you started SSI because you're like, "I think I have a way of approaching how to do this safely in a way that the other companies don't."
회사들과는 다르게 갖고 있다고
생각한다"는 마음이셨겠죠.
그 차이가 뭔가요?
What is that difference?
제가 설명하자면, 유망하다고
생각하는 아이디어들이 있고,
The way I would describe it is that there are some ideas that I think are promising and I want to investigate them and see if they are indeed promising or not.
그게 정말 유망한지 아닌지
검증해보고 싶다는 거예요.
정말 그만큼 단순해요.
It's really that simple.
하나의 시도인 거죠.
It's an attempt.
만약 이 아이디어들이 —
저희가 논의했던 일반화
If the ideas turn out to be correct—these ideas that we discussed around understanding generalization—then I think we will have something worthy.
이해에 관한 아이디어들
말이에요 — 옳다고 판명되면,
저희는 뭔가 가치 있는 걸
갖게 될 거라고 생각해요.
그게 옳다고 판명될까요?
Will they turn out to be correct?
저희는 연구를 하고 있어요.
We are doing research.
저희는 완전히 '연구의 시대' 회사예요.
We are squarely an "age of research" company.
진전을 이루고 있어요.
We are making progress.
사실 지난 1년간 꽤
좋은 진전을 이뤘지만,
We've actually made quite good progress over the past year, but we need to keep making more progress, more research.
계속 더 진전을 이루고
더 연구를 해야 해요.
제가 보는 방식은 그래요.
That's how I see it.
목소리를 내고 참여하려는
시도로 보고 있어요.
I see it as an attempt to be a voice and a participant.
공동창업자이자 전 CEO께서
최근 메타로 이직하셨는데,
Your cofounder and previous CEO left to go to Meta recently, and people have asked, "Well, if there were a lot of breakthroughs being made, that seems like a thing that should have been unlikely."
사람들은 이렇게 물어요.
"돌파구가 많이 나오고
있었다면, 그런 일이 일어나기는
어려웠을 것 같은데요."
어떻게 답하실지 궁금해요.
I wonder how you respond.
이 질문에 대해서는, 그냥 잊혀졌을 수도
For this, I will simply remind a few facts that may have been forgotten.
있는 몇 가지 사실을 상기시켜 드릴게요.
맥락을 보여주는 이 사실들이
상황을 설명해준다고 생각해요.
I think these facts which provide the context explain the situation.
맥락을 말씀드리면, 저희가 320억
달러 기업가치로 투자 유치를
The context was that we were fundraising at a $32 billion valuation, and then Meta came in and offered to acquire us, and I said no. But my former cofounder in some sense said yes.
하고 있었는데, 메타가 저희를 인수하겠다고
제안해왔고, 저는 거절했어요.
그런데 제 전 공동창업자는 어떤
의미에서는 그러겠다고 했죠.
그 결과 그도 상당한 단기
유동성을 누릴 수 있었고,
As a result, he also was able to enjoy a lot of near-term liquidity, and he was the only person from SSI to join Meta.
SSI 출신 중 유일하게
메타에 합류하게 됐죠.
SSI의 계획은, 초인적 지능을
갖게 되는 인류 역사상 아주
It sounds like SSI's plan is to be a company that is at the frontier when you get to this very important period in human history where you have superhuman intelligence.
중요한 이 시기에 프론티어에 서
있는 회사가 되는 것 같아요.
초인적 지능이 잘 풀리게 만들 방법에
대한 아이디어들이 있으신 거고요.
You have these ideas about how to make superhuman intelligence go well.
하지만 다른 회사들은 각자 자신들의
아이디어를 시도할 거고요.
But other companies will be trying their own ideas.
초지능이 잘 흘러가게 만드는
SSI만의 접근법은 뭐가 다른가요?
What distinguishes SSI's approach to making superintelligence go well?
SSI를 구분 짓는 가장
큰 건 기술적 접근법이에요.
The main thing that distinguishes SSI is its technical approach.
저희는 가치 있다고 생각하는 다른 기술적
We have a different technical approach that I think is worthy and we are pursuing it.
접근법을 갖고 있고,
그걸 추구하고 있어요.
결국엔 전략들의 수렴이 있을
거라는 입장은 변함없어요.
I maintain that in the end there will be a convergence of strategies.
AI가 더 강력해지면서 어느
시점엔, 전략이 어때야 하는지가
I think there will be a convergence of strategies where at some point, as AI becomes more powerful, it's going to become more or less clearer to everyone what the strategy should be.
모두에게 어느 정도 분명해지는 그런
수렴이 있을 거라고 생각해요.
아마 이런 모습일 거예요. 서로
대화할 방법을 찾아야 하고,
It should be something like, you need to find some way to talk to each other and you want your first actual real superintelligent AI to be aligned and somehow care for sentient life, care for people, democratic, one of those, some combination thereof.
최초의 진짜 초지능 AI는 정렬되어
있어야 하고, 어떻게든 지각
있는 생명을 소중히 여기고
사람들을 소중히 여겨야 하고,
민주적이어야 하고 — 이런 것들
중 하나이거나 그 조합이어야 해요.
이게 모두가 추구해야
할 조건이라고 생각해요.
I think this is the condition that everyone should strive for.
그게 바로 SSI가 추구하는 것이고요.
That's what SSI is striving for.
이번엔, 아직 아니라면, 다른
모든 회사들도 결국 같은
I think that this time, if not already, all the other companies will realize that they're striving towards the same thing.
걸 추구하고 있다는 걸
깨닫게 될 거라고 생각해요.
두고 봐야죠.
We'll see.
AI가 더 강력해지면 세상이
정말로 바뀔 거라고 생각해요.
I think that the world will truly change as AI becomes more powerful.
상황도 정말 달라지고, 사람들도 정말
I think things will be really different and people will be acting really differently.
다르게 행동하게 될 거라고 생각해요.
예측 얘기가 나왔으니
말인데, 말씀하신 그 시스템
Speaking of forecasts, what are your forecasts to this system you're describing, which can learn as well as a human and subsequently, as a result, become superhuman?
— 사람만큼 학습할 수
있고 그 결과로 초인간이
되는 시스템 — 에 대한
예측은 어떻게 되나요?
5에서 20 정도라고 생각해요.
I think like 5 to 20.
5년에서 20년이요?
5 to 20 years?
음.
Mhm.
세상이 어떻게 흘러갈지, 그
그림을 한번 풀어보고 싶어요.
I just want to unroll how you might see the world coming.
이런 거예요 — 앞으로
몇 년간은 다른 회사들이
It's like, we have a couple more years where these other companies are continuing the current approach and it stalls out.
지금 접근법을 계속
이어가다가 정체되는 거죠.
여기서 '정체된다'는 건 매출이 수천억
"Stalls out" here meaning they earn no more than low hundreds of billions in revenue?
달러 초반 수준을 넘지
못한다는 뜻인가요?
정체된다는 게 어떤
의미인지는 어떻게 보시나요?
How do you think about what stalling out means?
제 생각에 정체된다는 건… 아마 여러
I think stalling out will look like…it will all look very similar among all the different companies.
회사들 사이에서 다
비슷비슷해 보일 거예요.
그런 식일 수도 있어요.
It could be something like this.
확실치 않지만, 정체되더라도 이 회사들이
I'm not sure because I think even with stalling out, I think these companies could make a stupendous revenue.
엄청난 매출은 낼 수 있다고 봐요.
이익은 아닐 수도 있어요,
서로 차별화하려고
Maybe not profits because they will need to work hard to differentiate each other from themselves, but revenue definitely.
애써야 할 테니까요.
하지만 매출은 확실히요.
그런데 당신 모델을
보면, 결국 올바른 해법이
But something in your model implies that when the correct solution does emerge, there will be convergence between all the companies.
나오면 모든 회사가 수렴하게
된다는 뜻이잖아요.
왜 그렇게 생각하시는지 궁금해요.
I'm curious why you think that's the case.
제가 말한 건 정렬 전략에서의
수렴 쪽에 더 가까워요.
I was talking more about convergence on their alignment strategies.
기술적 접근에서도 결국
수렴이 일어나긴 할 것
I think eventual convergence on the technical approach is probably going to happen as well, but I was alluding to convergence to the alignment strategies.
같지만, 제가 암시한 건
정렬 전략의 수렴이었어요.
정확히 어떤 걸 해야 한다는 건가요?
What exactly is the thing that should be done?
미래가 어떻게 펼쳐질지에 대한
그림을 좀 더 잘 이해하고 싶어서요.
I just want to better understand how you see the future unrolling.
지금은 여러 회사가 있고, 그들의
접근법이 계속 매출은 내겠지만
Currently, we have these different companies, and you expect their approach to continue generating revenue but not get to this human-like learner.
이 인간 같은 학습자에는 도달하지
못할 거라고 보시는 거죠.
그럼 지금 회사들이 여러
갈래로 나뉘어 있는 셈이네요.
So now we have these different forks of companies.
당신이 있고, 씽킹 머신즈가
있고, 다른 랩들도 많고요.
We have you, we have Thinking Machines, there's a bunch of other labs.
그중 하나가 올바른 접근법을
찾아낼 수도 있고요.
Maybe one of them figures out the correct approach.
그런데 그 제품 출시가
다른 사람들에게 이걸
But then the release of their product makes it clear to other people how to do this thing.
어떻게 하는지 분명히 알려주게 되잖아요.
어떻게 하는지는 분명해지지
않을 것 같아요. 하지만 뭔가
I think it won't be clear how to do it, but it will be clear that something different is possible, and that is information.
다른 게 가능하다는 건 분명해지죠.
그리고 그게 정보예요.
그러면 사람들이 그게 어떻게
작동하는지 알아내려 하겠죠.
People will then be trying to figure out how that works.
다만 여기서 다뤄지지 않은
것 중 하나는, AI의
I do think though that one of the things not addressed here, not discussed, is that with each increase in the AI's capabilities, I think there will be some kind of changes, but I don't know exactly which ones, in how things are being done.
능력이 늘어날 때마다 일하는
방식에 어떤 변화가 생길
거라는 점이에요. 정확히 어떤
변화인지는 모르겠지만요.
중요할 거라고 생각하지만, 정확히 그게
I think it's going to be important, yet I can't spell out what that is exactly.
뭔지는 콕 집어 말씀드리기 어렵네요.
기본적으로 생각하면, 그
모델을 가진 회사가 이 모든
By default, you would expect the company that has that model to be getting all these gains because they have the model that has the skills and knowledge that it's building up in the world.
이득을 가져갈 거라고
예상하게 되잖아요. 세상에서
쌓아온 기술과 지식을 가진
모델을 갖고 있으니까요.
그 이득이 널리 분산될 거라고,
이 지속 학습 루프를 가장 먼저
What is the reason to think that the benefits of that would be widely distributed and not just end up at whatever model company gets this continuous learning loop going first?
돌리는 모델 회사한테만 돌아가지
않을 거라고 생각할 이유가 뭔가요?
제가 생각하기에 이런
일이 일어날 것 같아요.
Here is what I think is going to happen.
첫째, 지금까지 과거의 AI들이
어떻게 흘러왔는지 한번 보죠.
Number one, let's look at how things have gone so far with the AIs of the past.
한 회사가 진보를 만들어내면 다른
회사가 서둘러서, 어느 정도 시간이 지난
One company produced an advance and the other company scrambled and produced some similar things after some amount of time and they started to compete in the market and push the prices down.
뒤 비슷한 걸 만들어냈고, 그렇게
시장에서 경쟁하며 가격을 낮춰갔죠.
그래서 시장의 관점에서 보면, 거기서도
So I think from the market perspective, something similar will happen there as well.
비슷한 일이 일어날 거라고 생각해요.
그나저나 저희가 지금 얘기하는
건 '좋은 세상' 쪽이에요.
We are talking about the good world, by the way.
좋은 세상이란 어떤 모습인가요?
What's the good world?
그건 강력하고 인간 같은
학습자들이 있으면서 동시에…
It’s where we have these powerful human-like learners that are also…
그런데 말이죠, 초지능 AI의
스펙에서 아직 이야기하지 않은
By the way, maybe there's another thing we haven't discussed on the spec of the superintelligent AI that I think is worth considering.
게 하나 더 있는데, 고려해
볼 가치가 있는 것 같아요.
그건 좁게 만들 수도 있다는 거예요.
It’s that you make it narrow, it can be useful and narrow at the same time.
유용하면서 동시에 좁을 수 있다는 거죠.
좁은 초지능 AI를 여러
개 가질 수도 있어요.
You can have lots of narrow superintelligent AIs.
그런데 그런 게 여럿 있고, 그걸로
But suppose you have many of them and you have some company that's producing a lot of profits from it.
큰 수익을 내는 회사가 있다고 해보죠.
그럼 다른 회사가 들어와서
경쟁을 시작하는 거예요.
Then you have another company that comes in and starts to compete.
경쟁이 작동하는 방식은
전문화를 통해서예요.
The way the competition is going to work is through specialization.
경쟁은 전문화를 좋아하죠.
Competition loves specialization.
시장에서도 보이고,
진화에서도 마찬가지로 보여요.
You see it in the market, you see it in evolution as well.
다양한 니치들이 생기고,
각 니치를 차지하는
You're going to have lots of different niches and you're going to have lots of different companies who are occupying different niches.
서로 다른 회사들이 많이 생길 거예요.
이런 세상에서는 한 AI
회사가 정말 복잡한 경제
In this world we might say one AI company is really quite a bit better at some area of really complicated economic activity and a different company is better at another area.
활동의 어떤 영역에서 훨씬
뛰어나고, 다른 회사는
또 다른 영역에서 더
뛰어나다고 할 수 있겠죠.
그리고 세 번째 회사는
소송을 정말 잘하고요.
And the third company is really good at litigation.
그건 인간 같은 학습이 함의하는
것과 모순되지 않나요?
Isn't this contradicted by what human-like learning implies?
그러니까 그건 배울 수 있다는 거잖아요…
It’s that it can learn…
배울 수는 있죠, 하지만
축적된 학습이라는 게 있어요.
It can, but you have accumulated learning.
큰 투자가 들어가 있는 거죠.
You have a big investment.
이 일에 정말, 정말 잘하게, 정말
You spent a lot of compute to become really, really good, really phenomenal at this thing.
뛰어나게 되기까지
엄청난 컴퓨트를 썼어요.
다른 누군가는 또 다른 일에 정말 잘하게
Someone else spent a huge amount of compute and a huge amount of experience to get really good at some other thing.
되려고 엄청난 컴퓨트와
엄청난 경험을 썼고요.
그렇게 인간적인 학습을 많이
쏟아부어서 그 지점에 도달했는데,
You apply a lot of human learning to get there, but now you are at this high point where someone else would say, "Look, I don't want to start learning what you've learned."
이제 그 정점에 서면 다른 누군가는
이렇게 말하겠죠. "이봐,
난 당신이 배운 걸 나도
처음부터 배우고 싶지는 않아."
그럼 여러 회사들이 인간 같은
지속 학습 에이전트를 동시에
I guess that would require many different companies to begin at the human-like continual learning agent at the same time so that they can start their different tree search in different branches.
시작해서, 각자 다른 가지에서 트리
탐색을 시작해야 한다는 거네요.
그런데 한 회사가 그 에이전트를, 그
But if one company gets that agent first, or gets that learner first, it does then seem like…
학습자를 먼저 손에 넣으면, 그럼 왠지…
음, 경제 안의 모든 개별
직무를 생각해보면, 회사 하나가
Well, if you just think about every single job in the economy, having an instance learning each one seems tractable for a company.
그 각각을 학습하는 인스턴스를
두는 게 충분히 가능해 보여요.
타당한 논리예요.
That's a valid argument.
제 강한 직관으로는 이렇게
흘러가지 않을 것 같아요.
My strong intuition is that it's not how it's going to go.
그 주장대로라면 이렇게 흘러가겠지만, 제
The argument says it will go this way, but my strong intuition is that it will not go this way.
강한 직감은 그렇게 되지
않으리라는 거예요.
이론상으론 이론과 실제가 다르지 않죠.
In theory, there is no difference between theory and practice.
실제로는 다르지만요.
In practice, there is.
이것도 그런 경우 중
하나가 될 것 같아요.
I think that's going to be one of those.
재귀적 자기 개선에 대한 사람들의
모델 중 상당수는, 서버 안에
A lot of people's models of recursive self-improvement literally, explicitly state we will have a million Ilyas in a server that are coming up with different ideas, and this will lead to a superintelligence emerging very fast.
일리야가 100만 명 있어서 각자
다른 아이디어를 낸다는 걸 문자
그대로 명시하고, 이게 초지능의 아주
빠른 등장으로 이어진다고 말해요.
지금 하고 계신 일이 얼마나 병렬화
가능한지에 대한 직감이 있으신가요?
Do you have some intuition about how parallelizable the thing you are doing is?
일리야를 복제한다면,
거기서 얻는 이득은 뭘까요?
What are the gains from making copies of Ilya?
모르겠어요.
I don’t know.
분명 수확 체감이 있을
거라고 봐요. 똑같이 생각하는
I think there'll definitely be diminishing returns because you want people who think differently rather than the same.
사람보다는 다르게 생각하는
사람들을 원하니까요.
저를 그대로 복제한 존재들이
있다 해도, 거기서 점진적으로
If there were literal copies of me, I'm not sure how much more incremental value you'd get.
얼마나 더 가치를 얻을 수
있을지는 잘 모르겠어요.
다르게 생각하는 사람들,
그게 우리가 원하는 거예요.
People who think differently, that's what you want.
완전히 다른 회사에서, 어쩌면
겹치지 않을 법한 데이터셋으로
Why is it that if you look at different models, even released by totally different companies trained on potentially non-overlapping datasets, it's actually crazy how similar LLMs are to each other?
학습시킨 모델들인데도 서로 이렇게까지
비슷한 건 왜 그런 걸까요?
데이터셋들이 생각보다 더
많이 겹치는 걸 수도 있죠.
Maybe the datasets are not as non-overlapping as it seems.
하지만 한 사람 한 사람은
미래의 AI보다 생산성이
But there’s some sense in which even if an individual human might be less productive than the future AI, maybe there’s something to the fact that human teams have more diversity than teams of AIs might have.
낮을 수 있어도, 인간
팀이 AI 팀보다 다양성이
크다는 사실에는 분명
의미가 있을 것 같아요.
AI들 사이에서 의미 있는 다양성을
어떻게 이끌어낼 수 있을까요?
How do we elicit meaningful diversity among AIs?
그냥 temperature를 높이는
건 헛소리만 낳을 것 같아요.
I think just raising the temperature just results in gibberish.
그보다는 서로 다른 과학자들이
저마다 다른 편견이나
You want something more like different scientists have different prejudices or different ideas.
생각을 갖는 것 같은, 그런
종류의 다양성이 필요해요.
AI 에이전트들 사이에서 그런 종류의
다양성을 어떻게 얻을 수 있을까요?
How do you get that kind of diversity among AI agents?
지금까지 다양성이 없었던 이유는,
제 생각엔 사전학습 때문이에요.
So the reason there has been no diversity, I believe, is because of pre-training.
사전학습된 모델들이 다
거의 똑같은 건, 다들
All the pre-trained models are pretty much the same because they pre-train on the same data.
같은 데이터로 사전학습을 하기 때문이죠.
이제 RL과 사후학습에서부터
차별화가 나타나기 시작해요.
Now RL and post-training is where some differentiation starts to emerge because different people come up with different RL training.
사람마다 서로 다른 RL
훈련을 만들어내니까요.
예전에 셀프플레이를 힌트로
언급하신 적이 있었죠.
I've heard you hint in the past about self-play as a way to either get data or match agents to other agents of equivalent intelligence to kick off learning.
데이터를 얻거나, 학습을
촉발하기 위해 비슷한 수준의
지능을 가진 에이전트들끼리
맞붙게 하는 방법으로요.
그런데 LLM에 이런 방식이
통한다는 공개된 제안이
How should we think about why there are no public proposals of this kind of thing working with LLMs?
왜 없는지, 우리는 이걸
어떻게 생각해봐야 할까요?
두 가지를 말씀드리고 싶어요.
I would say there are two things to say.
제가 셀프플레이를 흥미롭다고
생각했던 이유는, 데이터 없이
The reason why I thought self-play was interesting is because it offered a way to create models using compute only, without data.
컴퓨트만으로 모델을 만들어낼
방법을 제공했기 때문이에요.
데이터가 궁극적인 병목이라고 본다면,
If you think that data is the ultimate bottleneck, then using compute only is very interesting.
컴퓨트만 쓰는 방식이 아주 흥미로워지죠.
그래서 그게 흥미로운 지점이에요.
So that's what makes it interesting.
문제는 셀프플레이가—적어도 과거에
하던 방식대로, 에이전트들이 서로
The thing is that self-play, at least the way it was done in the past—when you have agents which somehow compete with each other—it's only good for developing a certain set of skills.
경쟁하는 형태로는—특정 기술들을
기르는 데만 유용하다는 거예요.
너무 좁아요.
It is too narrow.
협상, 갈등, 특정 사회적 기술,
전략 수립 같은 데만 유용하죠.
It's only good for negotiation, conflict, certain social skills, strategizing, that kind of stuff.
그런 기술들이 중요하다면
셀프플레이가 유용할 거예요.
If you care about those skills, then self-play will be useful.
사실 셀프플레이도 자기 자리를 찾긴
했다고 봐요, 다른 형태로요.
Actually, I think that self-play did find a home, but just in a different form.
그러니까 토론이라든지 증명자-검증자,
혹은 여러분의 실수를
So things like debate, prover-verifier, you have some kind of an LLM-as-a-Judge which is also incentivized to find mistakes in your work.
찾아내도록 인센티브가 걸린
LLM-as-a-Judge 같은 것들이요.
정확히 셀프플레이는 아니지만,
관련된 적대적 구조라고 할
You could say this is not exactly self-play, but this is a related adversarial setup that people are doing, I believe.
수 있죠. 사람들이 실제로
하고 있는 방식이라고 봐요.
사실 셀프플레이는 에이전트 간의 더
일반적인 경쟁의 특수한 사례예요.
Really self-play is a special case of more general competition between agents.
경쟁에 대한 자연스러운 반응은
남들과 달라지려 하는 거죠.
The natural response to competition is to try to be different.
그러니까 여러 에이전트를 함께 두고
이렇게 말한다고 해보세요. "다들
So if you were to put multiple agents together and you tell them, "You all need to work on some problem and you are an agent and you're inspecting what everyone else is working," they’re going to say, "Well, if they're already taking this approach, it's not clear I should pursue it.
이 문제를 풀어야 하고, 너는
에이전트로서 다른 모두가 뭘 하고
있는지 보고 있어." 그러면 에이전트는
이렇게 말하겠죠. "음, 다들
이미 이 방식을 쓰고 있다면, 내가
이걸 따라야 할지 모르겠는데.
차별화된 걸 해야 할 것 같아."
I should pursue something differentiated."
그래서 이런 구조도 접근법의 다양성을
So I think something like this could also create an incentive for a diversity of approaches.
만들어내는 인센티브가
될 수 있다고 봐요.
마지막 질문이에요.
연구 감각이란 뭔가요?
Final question: What is research taste?
누가 봐도 세상에서 AI 연구
감각이 최고라고 여겨지는 분이잖아요.
You're obviously the person in the world who is considered to have the best taste in doing research in AI.
알렉스넷부터 GPT-3까지, 딥러닝
You were the co-author on the biggest things that have happened in the history of deep learning, from AlexNet to GPT-3 to so on.
역사상 가장 큰 사건들의 공동저자셨죠.
그게 뭔가요, 이런 아이디어들을 어떻게
What is it, how do you characterize how you come up with these ideas?
떠올리시는지 어떻게 설명하시겠어요?
제 경우에 대해서는 말씀드릴 수 있어요.
I can comment on this for myself.
사람마다 방식이 다르다고 생각해요.
I think different people do it differently.
저 개인적으로는, AI가 어때야
하는가에 대한 미학이 하나의
One thing that guides me personally is an aesthetic of how AI should be, by thinking about how people are, but thinking correctly.
기준이에요. 사람이 어떤 존재인지를
생각하되, 제대로 생각하는 거죠.
사람에 대해 잘못
생각하기는 아주 쉬운데,
It's very easy to think about how people are incorrectly, but what does it mean to think about people correctly?
사람에 대해 제대로
생각한다는 건 무슨 뜻일까요?
몇 가지 예를 들어볼게요.
I'll give you some examples.
인공 뉴런이라는 아이디어는 뇌에서 직접
The idea of the artificial neuron is directly inspired by the brain, and it's a great idea.
영감을 받은 거고, 훌륭한 아이디어예요.
왜일까요?
Why?
왜냐하면 뇌에는 여러
기관들이 있잖아요. 주름도
Because you say the brain has all these different organs, it has the folds, but the folds probably don't matter.
있고요. 근데 그 주름은
아마 중요하지 않을 거예요.
그럼 왜 뉴런은 중요하다고 생각할까요?
Why do we think that the neurons matter?
뉴런은 수가 많으니까요.
Because there are many of them.
왠지 맞는 느낌이 드는 거죠.
그래서 뉴런을 원하게 되고요.
It kind of feels right, so you want the neuron.
뉴런 사이의 연결을 바꿔줄 어떤
국소적 학습 규칙을 원하게 되죠.
You want some local learning rule that will change the connections between the neurons.
뇌가 그렇게 할 거라는 게
그럴듯하게 느껴지는 거예요.
It feels plausible that the brain does it.
분산 표현이라는 아이디어도 그렇고요.
The idea of the distributed representation.
뇌가 경험에 반응하니까, 우리 신경망도
The idea that the brain responds to experience therefore our neural net should learn from experience.
경험으로부터 학습해야 한다는 생각이요.
뇌는 경험으로부터 학습하니, 신경망도
경험으로부터 학습해야 한다는 거죠.
The brain learns from experience, the neural net should learn from experience.
스스로에게 묻게 되는 거예요,
이게 근본적인가 아닌가.
You kind of ask yourself, is something fundamental or not fundamental?
원래 어떤 모습이어야 하는가 하는 거요.
How things should be.
그런 게 저를 상당히 이끌어
왔다고 생각해요. 여러 각도에서
I think that's been guiding me a fair bit, thinking from multiple angles and looking for almost beauty, beauty and simplicity.
생각하고, 거의 아름다움을 찾는
거죠. 아름다움과 단순함이요.
추함, 추함이 들어설 자리는 없어요.
Ugliness, there's no room for ugliness.
아름다움, 단순함, 우아함, 그리고
뇌로부터 얻는 올바른 영감이죠.
It's beauty, simplicity, elegance, correct inspiration from the brain.
그 모든 게 동시에 존재해야 해요.
All of those things need to be present at the same time.
그것들이 많이 있을수록, 톱다운
신념에 더 확신을 가질 수 있어요.
The more they are present, the more confident you can be in a top-down belief.
톱다운 신념은 실험이 나를
반박할 때 버티게 해주는 거예요.
The top-down belief is the thing that sustains you when the experiments contradict you.
왜냐하면 데이터를 항상 신뢰한다면, 맞는
Because if you trust the data all the time, well sometimes you can be doing the correct thing but there's a bug.
걸 하고 있어도 버그가
있을 수 있으니까요.
근데 버그가 있다는 걸 모르는 거죠.
But you don't know that there is a bug.
버그가 있다는 걸 어떻게 알 수 있나요?
How can you tell that there is a bug?
계속 디버깅해야 할지, 아니면 방향이
How do you know if you should keep debugging or you conclude it's the wrong direction?
틀렸다고 결론내려야 할지 어떻게 아나요?
그게 톱다운이에요.
It's the top-down.
이렇게 될 수밖에 없다고
말할 수 있는 거죠.
You can say things have to be this way.
이런 건 반드시 작동해야 한다,
그러니 계속 가야 한다는 거예요.
Something like this has to work, therefore we’ve got to keep going.
그게 톱다운이고, 이 다면적인 아름다움과
That's the top-down, and it's based on this multifaceted beauty and inspiration by the brain.
뇌에서 얻는 영감에 근거한 거예요.
네, 오늘은 여기까지 하죠.
Alright, we'll leave it there.
정말 감사합니다.
Thank you so much.
일리야, 정말 감사드려요.
Ilya, thank you so much.
네.
Alright.
감사합니다.
Appreciate it.
정말 좋았어요.
That was great.
네, 즐거웠어요.
Yeah, I enjoyed it.
네, 저도요.
Yes, me too.